<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Arrowes against Babylon, or, Certaine quæries serving to a cleere discovery of the mystery of iniquity whereunto are added endeavours for reformation in saints apparrell : with some quæries for the people called Quakers / by John Pendarves.</title>
            <author>Pendarves, John, 1622-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54006</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27463</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09863778</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09863778</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44290</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54006)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44290)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1365:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Arrowes against Babylon, or, Certaine quæries serving to a cleere discovery of the mystery of iniquity whereunto are added endeavours for reformation in saints apparrell : with some quæries for the people called Quakers / by John Pendarves.</title>
                  <author>Pendarves, John, 1622-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 45 [i.e. 43], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Livewell Chapman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Endeavovrs for reformation in apparrell."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism.</term>
               <term>Clothing and dress --  Moral and ethical aspects.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>ARROWES AGAINST BABYLON. <hi>OR</hi> Certaine <hi>Quaeries</hi> ſerving to a cleere Diſcovery of the <hi>Mystery of Iniquity. Whereunto are added</hi> Endeavours for Reformation in Saints apparrell. <hi>With ſome Quaeries</hi> for the people called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> JOHN PENDARVES a well wiſher to <hi>Sion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Put your ſelves in array againſt Babylon round about, ſhoote at her, ſpare no arrowes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Jerem. 50.14. v.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>Flee out of the midſt of Babylon, and deliver every man his ſoule, be not cut off in her iniquity; for this is the time of the Lords vengeance, hee will render unto her recompence,
<bibl>
                           <hi>Jere. 51.6. v.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>And I heard another voyce from heaven, ſaying, Come out of her my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that yet pertake not of her ſins, and that yee receive not of her plagues,
<bibl>
                           <hi>Rev. 18.41 v.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>O Daughter of Babylon, who art to be deſtroyed, happy ſhall he be that rewardeth thee, as thou haſt ſerved us.
<bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal. 137.8. v.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> at the <hi>Crowne</hi> in <hi>Popes-head-Alley.</hi> 1656.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Epiſtle Dedicatory.</hi> To the precious Sonnes of <hi>Sion,</hi> who minde the work of their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and to all the faithfull, and beloved <hi>Servants of God, ſmall and great.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fall of <hi>Babylon</hi> being decreed in Heaven, and declared on Earth, and the time ſaid to be <hi>neare at hand</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>This is one of the things of which</hi> John <hi>ſaith,</hi> They muſt ſhortly come to paſſe, <hi>Rev:</hi> 1.1.8.</note>, ſo many hundred yeares agoe, as have paſt ſince the revelation was given to <hi>John</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Much neerer now.</note>; Why ſhould it be thought beſide the work of this day, to ſeek her down-fall? and to cry aloud unto Gods people to come out of her? Hath not God, and man of late yeares, appeared againſt her oppreſſing powers, ſpirituall, and civill, in theſe Nations? Her maine Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with their grand ſupporter, where are they? Did not the ſure word of Prophecy againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> take hold of them? ſince thoſe Pillars have been removed, hath not that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy building, been as a falling houſe, out of which many thouſands of Gods people have haſted forth? the Lord going before them by many wonderfull, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall providences, opening a wide doore unto them. If the remnant of old, <hi>who preferr'd Jeruſalem above their cheife joy</hi> (which holds forth a true Character of <hi>Sions</hi> lovers) were ſo bold in her behalfe, to tell the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Babylon</hi> to her face, <hi>Thou art to be deſtroyed,</hi> calling
<pb facs="tcp:44290:3"/>
them happy who ſhould be the Inſtruments to reward her cruelties to Gods people, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. If they ſpeak thus, whilſt yet remaining captives, let it not ſeeme ſtrange, if we, who are in ſo great a meaſure delivered, doe in the ſame ſpirit of faith, declare openly the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching fall of the daughter of myſticall <hi>Babylon;</hi> which (that wee may not ſhoote at rovers) I have in the enſuing <hi>Quaeries</hi> laboured to diſcover, the mother, and her daughter, the mark at which thoſe arrows are ſhott. The mother being more notorious for her bloody perſecutions, and filthy abominations, may ſoone be diſcovered; her daughter, having putt on a new dreſſe, appeares freſh coloured, and well-liking, and hath her lovers amongſt great, if not good men. They who drinke of her wine, and eate of her dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, praiſe her beauty, as ſhee is now reformed. Shee hath (it ſeemes) painted her face with more art, and better ſucceſſe, then <hi>Jezebell,</hi> or elſe ſome have had leſſe zeale then <hi>Jehu,</hi> who having no great power on his ſide, yet commanded <hi>(that)</hi> painted <hi>Jezebel</hi> to be thrown downe. With <hi>this</hi> Jezebel the daughter of <hi>Babylon,</hi> men formerly of great note for zeale, and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (preferring peace before purity<note n="c" place="margin">The wiſdome that is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove preferres purity before peace, <hi>Jam: 3.17.</hi> Its firſt pure, then peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath is quite contrary, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing truth under a pretence of peace: in that true wiſdome, they who have acted of old, and of late, are accounted trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </note>) become confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate to oppoſe a thorow reformation, who ſeeme well content with the old garment, ſome new peices put to it, which (as our Saviour ſaith) makes the rent worſe; they cannot beare to have the axe laid at the roote. How doe many in our dayes, like <hi>Herod,</hi> heare good men gladly, till their luſts and wills be croſt? their hearts cleave to ſome worldly intereſt, which, (being as the right eye) they will not part with. Such can take Law and Covenant in their mouth, pray and preach well, with much excellency of ſpeech, but their ſpirits may be diſcerned by this one thing, They like not to reform, or to be reformed, with a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:44290:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
reformation, which is the onely right reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to the word of God; to which our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Covenant binds us, as alſo (with ſubordination thereunto) to the example of the beſt reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; which are ſuch undoubtedly, as ſtand at greateſt diſtance from Antichriſtian pollutions. Is the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Nation ſo reformed? if not, why doe they not preſſe forward? Nay, doe not many ſit downe, and take up their reſt, as if they had attained, and as if the worke were perfected? Hath myſticall <hi>Babylon</hi> been raſed to the foundation thereof? If not, ought not that remnant of Gods people, who retaine their firſt zeale againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> to proceed to pray againſt her, as the remnant of the faithfull of old againſt the Children of <hi>Edom</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Is it not the duty of Gods elect to cry day and night for vengeance upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſee <hi>Luk. 18.1.7.</hi> and <hi>8</hi> verſes.</note>, Pſal. 137.7. <hi>Remember, O Lord, the Children of Edom, in the day of Jeruſalem: who ſaid, raſe it, raſe it, even to the foundation thereof;</hi> Let us take heede of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding ſuch prayers, though put up by godly men of like paſſions with us, to be the fruite of their paſſions, and peeviſhneſſe. If here were need of further Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for this work, and for the Saints zealous praying and declaring againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> in a right ſpirit, ſufficient might be offered (not onely to juſtifie the practiſe, but alſo to invite thereunto) from this one conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that the glory of God, and the comfort of his people are ſo highly concerned in her fall, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures largely ſhew. Oh what joyfull Hallelujahs ſhall be ſung by the Saints, when they ſhall ſee the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God on the great Whore which corrupted the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If men of great light ſee not how this matter concernes the glory of God, Is it not becauſe they ſtudy to promote their owne intereſt more then his? have they no better inſight into the things that make for their owne glory? It is the joy of my heart, in the midſt of many cauſes of griefe, that
<pb facs="tcp:44290:4"/>
God will forme, yea he is forming a people for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe which ſhall ſhew forth his praiſe<note n="e" place="margin">And the people which ſhall be created ſhall praiſe the Lord, <hi>Pſal. 102.18. Eſay 43.21.</hi>
                     </note>. The naked ſingle deſigne of the people of this new Creation ſhall be that the Lord, the Lord alone, may be exalted: which (if the Author know his heart) is the one thing aymed at in ſpending thoſe Arrowes upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> as alſo in thoſe endeavours for reformation in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, wherein oppoſition is made againſt one (not the leaſt) of her evills. That which is added in thoſe <hi>Quaeries</hi> to the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſerves for the diſcovery of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, tranſforming himſelfe into an Angel of light. It is no new thing for ſcornfull men to ſet light by plain teſtimonies againſt their abominations, and lay a ſnare for him that reprooveth in the gate<note n="f" place="margin">Iſay 29.20, 21.</note>, making a man an offender for a word; if ſuch ſhall count mee vile for this work, I ſhall not thinke it ſtrange. If the Lord ſhall make it appeare that the leaſt of the poore of his flock receive light, and reape benefit hereby, and give the glory to him; I ſhall rejoyce therein. Although my ſervice to Chriſt in this, or any thing I can doe, be but ſmall, I am comforted in beleeving that there ſhall a time come, and that its not farre off, when God ſhall reward his ſervants, not onely the great, but the ſmall<note n="g" place="margin">Rev. 11.18.</note>. The high eſteeme I have of the prayers of the Saints, together with a deepe ſence of my need of freſh ſupplyes of grace, put mee upon this humble ſuit to you, who are the ſeede of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that after your ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to the Lord for all Saints, hee may obtaine a ſpeciall remembrance, who is unworthy to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The leaſt of thoſe who follow the Lambe. <hi>J. P.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>A word of Exhortation, To the people of God in <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Deare Friends,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beſeech you in the bowells of Chriſt, conſider, that like as it was a ſingular act of Gods grace to warne <hi>Lott</hi> to come out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> when fire and brimſtone was ready to come downe upon that Citty: ſo is it now no leſſe but rather a more eminent act of his rich grace, to warne and wooe you to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly engaging you thereunto, (even as though he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you) by, and for all the intereſt he hath in you; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Come out of her my people,</hi> Rev. <hi>18.4.</hi> The mercy to you, may appeare farre greater, the judgement of God upon <hi>Sodom</hi> being more tolerable, then the grievous torments and ſpirituall plagues belonging to <hi>Babylon,</hi> whoſe ſins reach unto Heaven, <hi>Rev. 18.5.</hi> and her judgement is lifted up unto the skies, <hi>Jerem. 51.9.</hi> Herein is his great goodneſſe to you, that he hath not onely given you timely notice, before the Decree bring forth, but in this alſo, that he hath condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to afford many helpes in his Word for the diſcovery of <hi>Myſticall Babylon,</hi> which with ſo much ſerpentine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome transformes her ſelfe with ſuch faire pretences, that ſhee is leaſt ſuſpected to be what ſhee is, by moſt who dwell with her. That little light which the Lord hath lent me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Myſtery, I here impart it to you as your right, conſidering my ſelfe as in the body of Gods people one with you; though not ſo, in reſpect of a viſible orderly Church-ſtate and worſhip, wherein the name of God is greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.
<pb facs="tcp:44290:5"/>
Beware of that which is a common evill among the people in the broad way, whom you joyne hand withall; to ſpeake evill of the things they underſtand not.<note n="*" place="margin">Pet. 2.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Yee are bought with a price,</hi> be not yee in ſuch bondage to men, as not to try their way, opinions, and ſayings by the Spirit, and the word of God, whereby <hi>David</hi> was made to underſtand more then all his teachers, and more then the ancients, <hi>Pſal. 119.99, 100.</hi> Why ſhould it be thought unlikely that God ſhould reveale unto babes and ſucklings that which he hides from the wiſe and prudent. Oh read and weigh theſe Scriptures, <hi>Mat. 11.25. 1 Cor. 1.27, 28. Pſal. 8.2. Iſa. 29.14, 15.</hi> My bowells being troubled, and my ſoule in travell for your deliverance, I have as a learner by way of Quaerie, preſented divers weighty things, backt with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to your conſideration; whereof the meditation hath been ſweete to me, the Lord make the reading ſo to you. And whereas God doth and will by men as inſtruments call to his people to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> before her utter deſtruction, which is not farre off. As the day, which hath already daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned comes on upon us, wee may expect cleerer light, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter helpes. In the meane time, accept of, uſe, and improve ſuch as you have, and the Lord command his bleſſing, that his name may have glory. So prayes.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The Lords unprofitable ſervant.</hi> J. P.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44290:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>Arrowes againſt <hi>Babylon. OR</hi> Certaine <hi>Quaeries</hi> ſerving to a cleere Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the <hi>Mystery of Iniquity.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Quae:</hi> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether <hi>Iſraells</hi> going into <hi>Aegypt</hi> their bondage there, and their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, were not all typicall, to ſet forth the ſtate of the Church and people of God under the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament?</p>
                  <p>And whether this hath not been by the tongues and pens of all parties of the godly in <hi>England,</hi> who have publickly contended for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in Religion, of late yeares generally confeſſed, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and principally the head of that body, her Eccleſiaſticall powers, the Pope, with his Cardinalls, Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be not that <hi>Myſticall Babylon the Great, the Mother of Harlots;</hi> deſcribed in <hi>Rev:</hi> 17. who is ſaid to be <hi>the Whore ſitting upon many waters, commiting fornication with the Kings of the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Having in her hand a golden cup full of abominations</hi> &amp;c. <hi>drunken with the blood of Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus?</hi> And whether thoſe Characters with others there layd downe by the bleſſed Spirit of God for our information,<note place="margin">That the church of <hi>Rome</hi> is no true Church of Chriſt, have not divers Martyrs ſealed it with their blood. Reade <hi>Acts and Mon.</hi>
                     </note> doe alſo fitly agree, and may be applyed to any Church or State whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as to the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> And if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be <hi>Myſticall Babylon,</hi> then whether is ſhee any more worthy to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Syon,</hi> or a true viſible Church of God, then was <hi>Babylon</hi> of old her proper type?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whether the Church of <hi>England</hi> (the Nation conſidered as a Church) with the Parochiall Congregations, as Churches, be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44290:6"/>
not a Daughter of that <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Mother of Harlots? and their Miniſtry, in point of Ordination, the off-ſpring of the Pope? Have they at any time, even to this day, either by word in any ſolemne Declaration, or by practiſe in gathering a Church out of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as out of the world, diſclaimed that Church-ſtate which in its groſſeſt corruption was avowed and maintained by the Popiſh Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry and people of this Land in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes? Is it not apparent that ſome new peices onely have been put to that old gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that old Church ſtate, yea whilſt firſt the ſame, and ſince the like people without any viſible Marks of Converſion, with their Romiſh Baptiſme and Ordination of Miniſtry are ſtill retained? And whether the aforeſaid Characters in the ſecond <hi>Quaery</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Mother of Harlots the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and her Miniſtry, doe not in like manner, in their meaſure, appeare upon her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Nationall Church of <hi>England,</hi> and her Miniſtry?</p>
                  <p>If ſo, then</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whether is it not the duty of all Gods people in this Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Church, and in the Parochiall (pretended) Churches, to ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from that falſe Church-ſtate, and their profeſſed Church wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in all the exerciſes thereof; together with their Church-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, as they ſtand and act on the account of office in that falſe Church? And whether the Commands of God to his people to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Rev: 18. To flee out of the midſt of her, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51. To depart thence and touch no uncleane thing, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 52.11.<note place="margin">Let ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> at the Word read and weigh thoſe Scriptures quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this Quaery.</note> be not a ſufficient Scripture-warrant for their ſo doing? And whether Gods people neglecting to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> doe not thereby doe great diſſervice to the cauſe of Chriſt againſt Antichriſt, and expoſe themſelves by their diſobedience in this thing, to the danger of receiving of her plagues, by pertaking of her ſins? <hi>Rev:</hi> 18.4. <hi>v.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <note place="margin">This Quaery with the two following may afford ſome help to diſcerne the times; and to reſolve the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Queſtion what is the work of the day?</note>5. Whether the ſtrange and wonderfull providences of God in the late Warrs in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> have they not in their courſes (not in one ſingle act onely) agreed with his word, to cleere the call, and open the way, to his Saints to come out of <hi>Babylon?</hi> Hath not the Lord eminently appeared againſt King, Biſhop, and <hi>Scotch</hi>-Presbyter, who refuſed to let Gods <hi>Iſrael</hi> goe free from the hard bondage of a forced Conformity to the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Church-worſhip? And did not God (who put it into the heart of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> to give liberty to the <hi>Jewes</hi> to goe up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to build Gods houſe, <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.1.) put it alſo into the hearts of our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44290:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Rulers, after great and ſignall ſucceſſes given their Armies, to grant liberty to his people to walke according to their light without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint and confinement to the Pariſh-Churches? And was not the hand of God ſtrong upon them to vouchſafe that releaſe from our bondage, notwithſtanding the unceſſant provocations of ſome to compell us to their way? If wee aske our Fathers can they ſhew us, our Elders, can they tell us of ſuch a deliverance wrought out with ſo high a hand for Gods people in this Iſland?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Whether if wee look at inward impreſſions on the hearts of Gods praying people, (which when they agree with the word, and providences of God, are ſpeciall helps whereby to judge of our dutie, and the ſeaſon thereunto belonging) may we not obſerve how the hearts of Saints have, during the late warres,<note place="margin">
                        <p>Let ſuch as have loſt their firſt zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> remember from whence they are fallen and repent. The people had a minde to the work, as in the dayes of <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> Neh <hi>4.6.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Such are more like the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Hagar</hi> the bond wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, then <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> the free mother.</p>
                        <p>Some are ſo fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, that they will not heare a word of it. Doe not ſuch ſpeak and thinke evill of the things they know not.</p>
                        <p>Is it becauſe they have no need of this. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance? or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not living e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bury their dead? Are not many theeves, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, ſuch as are publickly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of ſuch offences, harbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiall Churches without any Church cenſure upon them? And if this be ſo, there is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle cauſe why they ſhould blame thoſe who leave ſuch a company of corrupt men. O horrible hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie!</p>
                        <p>Do not ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Miniſters act as if they were willing to ſlide out of their old way, not fai ely taking their leave, taking to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the ſhame of their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
                        <p>Let ſuch as ſpeake againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> take heed that they doe it in a right ſpirit.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Rev. 18.6. Jer. 15.14.</hi> Shall not the ſteps of the poore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> downe the lofty City <hi>Iſa 36.6.</hi> Even the ſteps of thoſe who walke by the footſteps of the flock?</p>
                     </note> been ſtirred up to a great zeale againſt the whore of <hi>Babylon?</hi> Hath not God caſt that falſe Church ſtate and worſhip, roote, and branch, out of the hearts and affections of very many of his people, who being dead to mens traditions, minde a pure way of worſhip, cleerely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering to them the confuſions and corruptions of that way, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to proteſt againſt it, and forſake it, though to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their credit and profit, ſuffering great oppoſition on that account from their neere relations? Have not few yeares brought out of that way many thouſands in this Land, who have turned their back to <hi>Babylon</hi> with their faces towards <hi>Syon,</hi> enquiring the way thitherward? And of thoſe who remaine behind, are not many held back by worldly intereſts, and ſlaviſh feare of man? The more ingenious of them bluſh to affirme (being driven to it in defence of their ſtaying there) that their Congregations are true Churches, either in reſpect of matter, or forme, yet ſome there are who are ſo affrighted with feare of errour, that they are not free to enquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the truth in this thing.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Whether the zealous and tedious labours of the Parliament and Synod for reforming of the Nationall Church-Diſcipline, hath not proved like the waſhing of a Blackmore, and anſwer not to that ſaying <hi>Wee would have healed Babylon, but ſhee is not healed?</hi> What followes, as the Saints duty then but to <hi>forſake her?</hi> Are not the people in their Pariſh-Congregations ſo incorrigible, that their Phyſitians deſpaire of the cure? In ſtead of cutting off the corrupt part, have they not even rejected (for ſome yeares) that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Excommunication which ſerves to keepe a true Church pure? If one wicked perſon muſt be caſt out with his wickedneſſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44290:7"/>
leaſt a little Leaven might leaven the whole lumpe may wee not thinke their lump is long ſince leavened who have in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations ſo long retained, as members, without rejection, ſo great ſwarmes of prophane ones? Is not their Nationall Church (if wee denominate them ought with reſpect to the greater number) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Cage of uncleane birds, and a hold of every ſoule ſpirit, then a true viſible Church of God, a ſpirituall houſe conſiſting of lively Stones? Some indeed exclude the rude rabble from parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the Supper, which is but one act of Church-worſhip; but, Doe not many profeſſing to be Miniſters of their Churches, make large ſhew of zeale for Ordinances, as if they ſtrained at a gnat, and yet in this thing eaſily ſwallow downe a Camell, taking no notice in any way of practiſe, of ſo great an Ordinance, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duely practiſed by a true Church, tends to the deſtruction of the fleſh, and the ſaving of the ſoule in the day of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.8? If men take not to themſelves the ſhame of theſe their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in the matter of worſhip, what grounds have they, or their followers, to beleive, that God will ſhew them the patterne of his houſe, the goings out, and commings in thereof, &amp;c. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.11.</p>
                  <p>And if theſe things be ſo,</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Whether then the Saints and ſervants of God ought not to declare the Nationall-Church of <hi>England, (viz.</hi> the Nation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to be a Church) to be indeed no Church of Chriſt, but a Daughter of <hi>Babylon?</hi> And is it not their duty to diſcover her abominations, in ſuch Language (in ſpeaking of <hi>Babylon,</hi> either the Mother or her Daughter) as the Spirit of God makes uſe of, and commends to us in the holy Scriptures? Doth not that command to Gods people, to <hi>reward her as ſhee hath rewarded them,</hi> extend to a full reward, both in words, and deeds? And if through flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of men, ſlaviſh feare, or fooliſh pitty, Gods Archers (his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters) withhold to ſhoote ſuch arrowes againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or printing, as God hath put into their Quiver for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, may they not be juſtly rebuked for it?</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Whether a bare forſaking of the Nationall Church, and a verball declaring againſt it, be a ſufficient witneſſe-bearing for Chriſt, againſt Antichriſt, in the matter of Worſhip? or whether beſides all this, are not Gods people called by a bold profeſſion, and viſible practiſe of the ordinances of Chriſt, according to the Goſpel pattern, to hold forth a true Baptiſme, &amp; Church-worſhip,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44290:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſo by a contrary practiſe, to beare their teſtimony in the ſtrength of Gods Spirit, and truth, againſt that falſe way? And in ſo doing, though the worke of <hi>Zions</hi> building, may appeare, now in its beginning, as nothing, in compariſon of that glorious patterne in the Apoſtles dayes, is there not ground to beleive God will vouchſafe his preſence and helpe to his people in the work, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his good word, <hi>Haggai</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3? And when the Saints come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ought they not then to call upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to flow to <hi>Zion,</hi> and there to declare the worke of the Lord? <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.6.9, 10. And if this be the ſeaſon for the former duty, why not for the latter and having with, and amongſt them, the Word, and Spirit, according to that ſtable Covenant to beleivers in all generations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.21.<note place="margin">Neh. 2.18.</note> What hinders but they ſhould riſe and build?</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Whether many zealous Miniſters and people in the Pariſh-way, by reaſon of their ignorance of the times, and ſeaſons, and the great worke of God at this day, to bring his people out of Myſticall <hi>Babylon;</hi> may they not be in danger of fighting againſt God, and kicking againſt the pricks; as did many devout <hi>Jewes,</hi> who were zealous of the old legall Worſhip, not knowing or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the time of reformation from Jewiſh rudiments,<note place="margin">Heb 9.10.</note> was come? And, doe not many now as they then, little conſider Gods call to his people to reforme thorowly from all Antichriſtian pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, and to touch no uncleane thing, in this day of the Lords controverſie for <hi>Sion?</hi> And may wee not ſee, as then, ſo now, the things which God winked at in times of ignorance, hee will not winke at, but witneſſe againſt in times of light? And is there not a very great ſecurity upon many profeſſors,<note place="margin">Can yee not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the ſignes of the times? <hi>Mat. 16.3.</hi>
                     </note> and darkneſſe upon their right eye, that notwithſtanding all the ſignes of the times, and all the late wonderfull workes of God, they are not awakened to diſcerne, and doe the ſpeciall duties, which God by his ſtrange diſpenſations calls them to? And is it not apparent, that many who ſhould inſtruct others in the duty of the day,<note place="margin">It is the duty of the wiſe Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to give the Children of God the portion of Doctrine ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the ſeaſon. <hi>Luk. 12 42.</hi>
                     </note> doe diſcourage them from enquiring into ſuch things, telling them of the danger of miſtakes, and the great difficultie of finding out truth, referring them in many things to the footeſteps of the flock in times of Popiſh darkneſſe? But is it not high time for Gods people to goe a ſtep beyond ſuch Watch-men, enquiring after Chriſt in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcovery of truth? And ſeeing God hath <hi>choſen the weake and fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe,</hi> ought not even ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44290:8"/>
to ſearch into the booke of revelation, ſeeking God by faithfull fervent prayer, for his promiſed Spirit to lead them into all truth, remembring the words of <hi>David, Thou through thy precepts haſt made me wiſer then mine enemies, I have more underſtanding then all my teachers,</hi> Pſal. 119.98, 99.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Whether the Pariſh-Miniſtry in their ſtanding, and acting, as ſuch, are not found taking part with <hi>Babylon,</hi> and warring againſt the true viſible Churches of Chriſt, and all others who withdraw from and witneſſe againſt the Common polluted way of worſhip? And if ſo, whether thoſe who are enlightened, may warrantably upon the account of the gifts and godlineſſe of ſuch Teachers fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after them, ſo as to have fellowſhip with them in their broad Church-way? And is it not to make Idolls of them, and preferre them before Chriſt, and ſet them above him, if they chooſe rather to follow after ſuch Miniſters in that way which hath no word of God for it, then to follow Chriſt in that deſpiſed way of worſhip, which hath the ſure word of Scripture for its warrant?<note place="margin">Mark how Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan makes uſe of Eminent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Deſignes.</note> If <hi>Peter</hi> that eminent Preacher, might be, and was ſo farre captivated by the Tempter, as to oppoſe by rebuking Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe, when he ſpake of his ſuffering death, <hi>Mat:</hi> 16 21, 22, 23. And againe denied him ſhamefully when he came to ſuffer, with curſing and oathes, ſaying he never knew the man; And after all this at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time the ſame <hi>Peter</hi> who was ſo famous an inſtrument in Gods hand for converting ſo many ſoules, even he becomes a miſleader in a way of diſſimulation, <hi>Gal:</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. ſo that <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> an eminent Miniſter of Chriſt,<note place="margin">If ſome who ſee ſuch diſſembling tell them that diſſemble, that they are to be blamed, they do but as <hi>Paul</hi> did who told <hi>Peter</hi> of his fault. <hi>Gal. 2.14.</hi>
                     </note> and divers others were carried away with his diſſimulation. If ſo it were with <hi>Peter,</hi> is there not ground enough for the good people in that way to feare, that their Miniſters, even the choiceſt of them, may be fallen into temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be prejudic't againſt the worke of a thorow-reformation, ſeeing their preferments, livings, and honours ſeeme to be ſtruck at; and ſo being offended, labour to draw in others to be one with them, in their offence and oppoſition againſt the Saints in their preſent warfare for Chriſt againſt Antichriſt?</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Whether the greater number of people in the Pariſh-Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyes, are not in danger of eternall Damnation, through their high preſumption that they are in Chriſt, and in a good eſtate? And whether have not <hi>Englands</hi> Church-Miniſtry much to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for, who have begotten, and cheriſhed this confidence in them, by declaring them in their old Catechiſme, <hi>To be regenerate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44290:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in their Baptiſme, made Members of Chriſt, and inheritors of the kingdome of Heaven?</hi> If this be true, and no lye they have taught them who thus exalted them unto heaven, may they not boldly conclude from many promiſes to beleevers, that their ſoules are in a ſafe condition? But it may now be ſaid, they have laid by that Catechiſme, and now they preach to them a neceſſitie of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; But ſeeing they have been trained up from their infancy in this beleife, which they have by heart, as wee ſay, that they were regenerate in their Baptiſme long wnce; Is it probable that the old evill ſent which hath remained in the veſſell, for ſo many yeares, will be removed by telling them now, and then, they muſt be borne againe? Although many declare this to them in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, and ſo wound them a little for the preſent time, yet doe they not quickly heale them againe at the Font, or Baſon,<note place="margin">Is not this to juſtifie the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked? that evill condemned <hi>Prov. 24.24.</hi>
                     </note> accepting them there for beleevers, by adminiſtring that to the children of all or moſt of them, that which they declare to be the priviledge of the Children of godly beleeving Parents? Doth not this eaſily help them to conclude, that whatſoever they ſay in preaching, their Miniſters by their practiſe declare them to be beleevers? And have their Miniſters notwithſtanding ſo much talke of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, at any time, plainely, ſolemnly, and openly declared their repentance for this their ſin, or the ſin of their predeceſſors in this thing, whereby they have deluded thouſands of ſoules? Have they declared it ſo, that the common people might run, and read their meaning? ſhould not the playſter be made as broad as the ſoare?</p>
                  <p>If ſo then</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Would it not be a praiſe-worthy deed, and that which would much tend to free the preſent Pariſh-Miniſtry from being guilty of the blood of their people, for them to confeſſe openly, the great ſin of their predeceſſors, and their ſin, ſo far as they have partaken with them, in declaring the people to be borne againe in Baptiſme, and made inheritors of the kingdome of heaven, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the danger of this horrid deluſion, giving them plainly to underſtand, that they, the generality among them, who ſay they are Chriſtians, are not ſuch, but are of the world, as appeares by their hatred of thoſe whom God hath choſen out of the world? And ſhould they not doe well to informe the godly among them, that they are in no viſible orderly Church-ſtate, provoking them to ariſe and meaſure the patterne, and ſending them forth by the footſteps of the flocks in the primitive times? and would it not well
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44290:9"/>
become them having thus borne their teſtimony in word againſt the aforeſaid evill, to back the ſame in their practiſe with a plaine deniall to adminiſter any Ordinance of Chriſt to the common mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, more then ſuch as are for converſion, which belong to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and Publicans,<note place="margin">Luk. 6.44.</note> till they ſee them bring forth fruits meet for repentance,<note place="margin">
                        <p>Good and bad men muſt be knowne by their fruit. <hi>Luk 6.44.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Pariſh people are a people of mans forming by ſuch meanes.</p>
                     </note> whereby a man may probably know, and warrantably judge them to be converted and brought to the moſt holy faith of Chriſt? And as for their preſent profeſſion taught them by the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of fathers, and by the cuſtomes and precepts of men, not by the mighty power of God through the Word, what ſolid ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction can it adminiſter whereon to ground a probable judgement that they are in the faith, Conſidering that in this Land, there is now no perſecution as in the Apoſtles dayes, but on the contrary, many worldly advantages attending the common profeſſion of Chriſt? And except ſome ſuch effectuall courſe be taken, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore commended in this <hi>Quaery,</hi> can the Miniſters of ſuch a people by all their faire gloſſes and ſubtill arguings acquitt themſelves from the blood of ſoules? Is it not their duty to take up the ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks out of the way of their people? Are not many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of poore ignorant ſoules, by looking at ſuch things as theſe, their ſuppoſed Chriſtning, and Church-ſtate, together with their dead ſaith, hindered from receiving Chriſt, and ſtrongly armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſight and ſence of a loſt eſtate, to their eternall undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Shall God make inquiſition for the blood of mens bodies, and ſhall he not one day make inquiſition for the blood of ſoules, and require it of thoſe who have holpen them to, and ſtrengthened them in ſuch deluſions?</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <p>Woe to them that call evill good. <hi>Iſay 5.20.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>If that old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Quod fieri non debet factum valet,</hi> will juſtifie ſuch an unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full act, why may it not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any other act of will-worſhip when it is done?</p>
                     </note>14. And if ſo,</p>
                  <p>Whether the Miniſtry and people in ſome Congregations ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Pariſh way, may not doe well to conſider, whether they be not found acceſſary to the aforeſaid great tranſgreſſion of the Parochiall Miniſtry, in juſtifying the ſprinckling of ungodly prophane and Popiſh Parents Children, as a ſufficient obedience to Chriſts command of Baptiſme, doctrinally diſcharging from the obligation of that command the conſciences of ſuch of their Members as have no other viſible Baptiſme? Is not this to call evill good, will-worſhip ſervice to Chriſt, and by mans tradition to make a command of God of none effect? Doe they not by ſuch a practiſe, though themſelves refuſe to ſprinckle ſuch Children, yet ſtrengthen the hands of thoſe who doe? And whether this be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44290:9"/>
not more then a touching, even the retaining an unclean thing, forbidden to thoſe who come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the command requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to deſtroy her utterly, <hi>Let nothing of her be left,</hi> Jer. 50.26. Whileſt this unlawfull ſprinckling of the ſeed of the ungodly is thus ſet up, may it not ſtand in their way as an obſtruction to the ſight and acknowledgement of the truth, concerning the true viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Baptiſme?<note place="margin">Can it be true Baptiſme accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to rule without a right viſible ſubject?</note> And whether all their arguing to prove that ſprinckling before ſpoken of (which themſelves ſay hath not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for it) to be ſufficient obedience to the command, be not that which will be found wood, hay, and ſtubble, when every mans worke ſhall be tryed by fire?</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Whether the unwarrantable mixture of Legall and Goſpel-worſhip and worſhippers, accounting this Nation a Church after the likeneſſe of the Jewiſh Nation, not by regeneration,<note place="margin">Antichriſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to forme a falſe Church.</note> but by fleſhly generation, gathering together into a pretended Church-body the viſibly Godly with the ungodly, withall promoting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine tythes, offerings, conſecrated places, Altars, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like Jewiſh Ceremonies, which were typicall,<note place="margin">The Prieſthood being changed, there is made of neceſſitie a charge alſo of the Law. <hi>Heb. 7.12.</hi>
                     </note> and to ceaſe in Goſpel-dayes; the joyning with all theſe a ſhew of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of breaking bread, and Baptiſme? Whether, (I ſay) may not ſuch a mixt worſhip, and the worſhippers be fitly termed <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> or confuſion? And whether to eſtabliſh ſuch a worſhip be not to deny in a Myſtery (as doth Antichriſt, Chriſts greateſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed friend) that Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.3.</note> the ſubſtance of the Legall ſhaddowes is come in the fleſh?<note place="margin">See <hi>Quae:</hi> the third.</note> And whether the pretended reformed Church of <hi>England</hi> retaining the old Romiſh Church-ſtate, and confuſed mixtures, maintaining the ſame things in ſubſtance with them, be not to be eſteemed as a painted <hi>Jezebel?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">16. Whether the <hi>Myſtery of iniquity</hi> which wrought in <hi>Pauls</hi> time, were not the ſame which now workes in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her Daughter-Churches? Did it not then worke mainely, to bring the Saints back under the bondage of <hi>Moſes</hi> his killing doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine; and his rudiments, and ſhaddowes? And whether the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle as a faithfull Witneſſe and Watchman did not bend his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines and diſcourſes in his Epiſtles, eſpecially to the <hi>Romans, Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> and <hi>Galatians,</hi> againſt this way of confounding the grace of God with mans works in juſtification, and confounding <hi>Moſes</hi> his old Lawes with Chriſts New Teſtament Ordinances? The ſame my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery being at worke now, not onely in <hi>Rome,</hi> but in this Nationall Church, Is it not the duty of Gods faithfull Miniſters, and Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44290:10"/>
to warre againſt it, by preaching, and diſcourſe, with the ſharp ſword of Chriſts Word, warning Gods people to beware of being ſeduced with this iniquity, which being diſcovered in many things more groſſe putts on a new dreſſe and works moſt myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, ſo that the workmen ſay, <hi>who ſeeth us?</hi> Iſa. 29.15.</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <note place="margin">The myſtery of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> is now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>17. Whether the <hi>Myſtery of iniquity</hi> that now workes be not founded upon the will of man, confederate with Satan? And is it not promoted, and upheld by humane and Serpentine wiſdome, with worldly power and pollicy, oppoſing and counter-working the Goſpel-graces of God, and Spirit of Chriſt, exalting the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture above the Creator? And whether the Abettors and promoters of this Myſtery, may not be diſcovered and diſcerned in our dayes, by their prizing men much more for their naturall, and acquired parts and abilities, then for the anointing, looking more at a mans learning, and prudence, then at the teachings of the Spirit, minding excellency of ſpeech more then the power of godlineſſe, ſeeking more after their owne honour from men, then to bring honour and glory to God?</p>
                  <p n="18">18. If ſo then,</p>
                  <p>May wee not well expect that God who hath laid by ſo many inſtruments, whoſe deſigne is to exalt his owne grace, his Son, and Spirit, will chooſe and uſe moſt unlikely inſtruments in mens ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, as the weake and fooliſh, in reſpect of worldly wiſdome, even the younger brethren, even as <hi>David</hi> amongſt the ſons of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> ſpiriting them through faith and prayer to bring to paſſe thoſe things which by humane power and pollicy could not be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected? Whether then are not many (and ſome good men) like to be deceived, who looke as did <hi>Samuel</hi> on <hi>Eliah,</hi> on ſome wiſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert, prudent men to be the onely prime inſtruments for Gods great and ſtrange worke,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26, 27, 28.</note> which will not be done by power or might, but by the Spirit of God? <hi>Zach:</hi> 4.6.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. Whether the faith and prayers of Gods people were not once as the Chariot-wheeles to the great worke of God in this Nation, but now of late ſince our enemies have been ſubdued, have not many good men ſlacked their hands to thoſe duties, and by looking and leaning to mans wiſdome, power and pollicy, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aſide to crooked wayes, and ſo have loſt the footſteps of the Lord in his worke? And whether can they come to a cleere ſight of them againe, except they humble themſelves and returne to a diligent exerciſe of faith and prayer? And if they will not be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44290:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
provoked thereunto, may it not be juſt for God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them unto ſore ſtraites, that ſo they may learne to ſeeke him early? <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. Whether the continuance of divers godly men in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and pertaking with her, be not one great occaſion of ſtumbling many weake Chriſtians, with ſome other enquirers after truth? And ought not ſuch then in the feare of God, to conſider and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine their ſtanding, and to lay to heart how great ſervice they doe to Antichriſt, and diſſervice to Chriſt, and his cauſe? And doth not the deceiver ſuck no ſmall advantage from godly men ſerving his deſigne which puts a faire face thereon, though they doe it ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly or inconſiderately? May we not obſerve that ſince god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is in ſome requeſt, Satan puts on ſuch a dreſſe as may moſt take with the godly to ſeduce them? And if theſe ſhould flee out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> would ſhee not ſoone appeare to all good men to be what ſhee is, and the judgements of God would they not come ſuddainly upon her, as did the fire and brimſtone upon <hi>Sodome</hi> the day that <hi>Lot</hi> came out? Whether that which hinders many from comming out, be not a ſlaviſh feare of man, and the flattery and friendſhip of this world? Whether ſuch onely will not be found fit to follow the Lambe even whither ſoever he goeth, who firſt ſit downe and count the coſt, and ſo build the Tower of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion upon Gods grace alone, as held out in his Covenant, truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with all their concernments? If they onely are ſaid to overcome who loved not their lives unto the death, as <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. What becomes of all the other profeſſors,<note place="margin">Remember the hand of God againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious <hi>Scots</hi> at <hi>Dunbar.</hi>
                     </note> the fearefull and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, &amp;c? If Gods ſervants ſhall abide there, notwithſtanding all the warnings they have had, and all Gods patience towards them, may he not juſtly ſlay them with the wicked, though he ſave their ſoules at the laſt?</p>
                  <p n="21">21. Whether the Antichriſtian Miniſtry in the Nations, which derive their Church-ſtate from <hi>Rome,</hi> are not found committing fornication with the Kings of the earth?<note place="margin">No Biſhop, No King.</note> And whether this forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation be not by interweaving their intereſts, for the upholding one another: thus by flatteries and by force bringing the people and keeping them in bondage to their wills, enſlaving their bodyes and inſnaring their ſoules?</p>
                  <p n="22">22. Whether ſeeing the greateſt judgements belong to <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> may not God in juſtice to aggravate their ſins who receive not the love of truth, lend them ſo much light as that many of them
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44290:11"/>
ſhall be found willfull Apoſtates, after all their other perſecutions, at length perſecuting the Spirit of Chriſt, ſo bringing upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſwift deſtruction? Are not many found perſecuting that light which they once profeſt? Is not that word made good in them, <hi>They ſhall goe and fall backward, and be broken, and ſnared, and taken?</hi> and if it be ſo, is it not high time to bid them take heede, leſt they ſin willfully after they have received the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth?</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Whether by that ſure rule of juſtice that all the blood from <hi>Abel</hi> ſhould come upon the perſecuting generation in Chriſts time, <hi>Math.</hi> 23.34, 35. And that in the <hi>Revel:</hi> 18.24. that in <hi>Babylon</hi> was found the blood of all the Saints ſhed from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the earth; Doth there not lye a heavy load of blood-guilt upon the Antichriſtian faction, who ſtrike in with that deadly intereſt at the latter end of the day, to act their part againſt Chriſt and his Cauſe? Should not all men take heede how they touch or take part with that intereſt, leaſt they come under the guilt of all the former bloody perſecutions of Gods Saints? Whether are not the oppoſite intereſts of fleſh and Spirit now at warre, the ſame intereſts which were at variance in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abell,</hi> the ſeeds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame two as formerly, though brought forth in ſeverall ages, though the controverſie betwixt them not alwayes upon the ſame part or point of truth or errour.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>ENDEAVOVRS FOR REFORMATION IN APPARRELL. <hi>OR</hi> Some reaſons rendred for Saints for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to put upon their Garments ſuch trimmings and ornaments as are alltoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperfluous, and apparently uſeleſſe. <hi>With Anſwers to ſeverall Objections.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Put on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make no proviſion for the fleſh, to fullfill the luſts thereof,
<bibl>
                           <hi>Rom. 13.14.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, the Lord ſaith, Becauſe the Daughters of Sion are haughty, and walke with ſtretched forth necks, wanton eyes, walking and mincing (or tripping nicely) as they goe, and making a tinckling with their feete. <hi>Iſa. 3.16.</hi> Therefore the Lord will ſmite with a ſcab the crowne of the head of the Daughters of Sion, &amp;c.
<bibl>
                           <hi>verſ. 17.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>In that day the Lord will take away the bravery of their tinckling ornaments, &amp;c.
<bibl>
                           <hi>verſ. 18.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>Behold the day commeth which ſhall burne as an Oven, and all the proud, and all that doe wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble, and that day that commeth ſhall burne them up, (ſaith the Lord) that it ſhall leave them neither roote nor branch,
<bibl>
                           <hi>Mal. 4.1.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>If yee will not heare, my ſoule ſhall weepe in ſecret places for your pride,
<bibl>
                           <hi>Jer. 13.17.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewell Chapman</hi> in <hi>Popes-head Alley.</hi> 1656.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:12"/>
                  <p>I ſhall gladly ſubmit to the judgement of ſuch touching theſe following Endeavours; knowing full well that they dare not ſo turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberately, to ſlight on the account of liberty, the leaſt hint of truth, clearely convincing them of duty; yet ſeeing ſuch may be tempted (for a worldly intereſt) to ſtifle their light in this thing, my Counſell is that they bare in minde the great price of their Redemption from a vaine converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which if they doe, they will not thinke it much to ſuffer loſſe in their names, and trades, for righteouſneſſe ſake in this fiery trying day; which is growne ſo darke to ſome, who not long ſince rejoyced in the light, that now they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine in the words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah 59.9. We waite for light, but behold obſcurity, &amp;c.</hi> Whilst knowledge ſeemes to be deſired, is not doing omitted? And are there not many, who will not ſee the things they have no minde to practiſe? But precept muſt be upon precept, line upon line, here a little, and there a little, that they may goe, and fall backward (as men doe who begin to reforme, and then when their intereſt is ſtruck at fall backward) and be broken, ſnared, and taken, <hi>Iſa. 28.13.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi> I ſhall not hide from thee the riſe of this diſcourſe, and the occaſion of its publication. The Lord having eminently appeared to a conſiderable number of his people in their waiting on him, together in ſeverall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Meetings, clearely witneſſing to their Conſciences againſt their ſuperfluous ornaments on their apparrell, in ſo much as diverſe did forthwith repent, and reforme; Some calling for a reaſon for this reformation, I thought it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (to avoyde much ſpeaking of this matter) to put pen to paper; and ſince that (to prevent the labour of tranſcribing Copies) to put my papers to the preſſe: If God teach thee to profit by them, give him alone the glory. As for ſcorners, let them delight in ſcorning; but let the wiſe heare the whole matter, and then give judgement.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:44290:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>And as for ſuch who are ſtrong, and by reaſon of uſe, have their ſenſes exerciſed to a cleere diſcerning between good and evill, let ſuch beare with my rude Endeavours, and bring forth a better teſtimony againſt that abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of pride in apparrell, wherewith most profeſſors are ſo ſpotted, and the profeſſion of godlineſſe, by reaſon thereof, ſo much evill ſpoken of, that if all ſhould hold their peace, a man might expect, according to the words of Chriſt in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe; <hi>Luk. 19.40. The ſtones would immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately cry out;</hi> Who knowes, but the leaſt of the flock, by an holy zeale (accompanied with many infirmities, which love ſhould cover) may provoke ſome great Preachers to looke more narrowly into this matter?<note place="margin">Rom. 2.14.</note> and to examine themſelves, why (ſeeing there was never more occaſion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to declare against pride) they have no more diſcovered this iniquity, which now it is to be feared, they winke at in others, becauſe ſo much of it cleaves to themſelves, and theirs; The Lord, who is faithfull and true, hath promiſed, <hi>That he will purely purge away all the droſſe of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and take away all her tinne; then will he reſtore unto them Judges as at the firſt, and Councellers as at the beginning,</hi> Iſai. <hi>1.25, 26.</hi> Which good thing that the Lord may ſpeedily performe, is the hearty deſire, and dayly prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The Lords moſt unworthy ſervant, whom he hath pluckt as a brand out of the fire. JOHN PENDARVES.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:13"/>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:44290:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>ENDEAVOVRS FOR REFORMATION IN APPARRELL. <hi>OR</hi> Some Reaſons rendred for Saints forbearing to put upon their Garments ſuch trimmings and ornaments as are all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſuperfluous, and apparently uſeleſſe. <hi>With Anſwers to ſeverall Objections.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt reaſon, or argument,<note place="margin">Firſt Ground or Reaſon.</note> takes its riſe from the death and reſurrection of Chriſt, and the Saints fellowſhip with him in both; and firſt, from his death; The Croſſe of Chriſt is that by which every true beleever is taught with <hi>Paul</hi> to be crucified to the world; and that not onely, as his faith preſents to him the glory of a crucified Chriſt, hidden from an eye of ſence,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14. 1 Pet. 2.11. Tit. 2.11, 12. 1 Pet. 1.8, 9.</note> farre exceeding all outward worldly glory; but alſo, as it teacheth him to warre againſt all ſenſuall worldly luſts, in confidence that Chriſt dyed to redeeme him from them. And herein doth the vertue and glory of the ſufferings of Chriſt on the Croſſe,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.6, 7, 8.</note> (wherein he is commended to us as amoſt glorious patterne of ſelfe-deniall) eminently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in his followers in crucifying the luſts of the fleſh the luſts of the eyes,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note> and pride of life;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.4.</note> all which ſtand in oppoſition to that newneſſe of life Saints are called to walke in. Now ſeeing the luſts of the fleſh were found warring againſt Chriſt on the Croſſe, and doe dayly warre againſt his Spirit in the hearts of Saints; and Chriſt warred and doth warre againſt them;<note place="margin">Gal. 5.17. Rom. 13.14.</note> his Souldiers ought not to make proviſion for them by ſuch ſuperfluous deckings, leaſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44290:14"/>
in ſo doing they be found feeding and cloathing Chriſts enemies, whilſt they neglect to feede and cloath his members; and leaſt thereby they obſcure or hide the glorious power of the death of Chriſt, which ſhould appeare to the eyes of all men in the viſible ſelfe-deniall of beleevers<note n="(a)" place="margin">What is there that is more viſible to all that behold the Saints then their apparrell. <hi>Phil 3.20.</hi>
                     </note>.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, As in conſideration of his death, the Saints are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to dye to this world, ſo with reſpect to his reſurrection, all thoſe who are riſen with him, ought to ſeeke thoſe things which are above, <hi>Col:</hi> 3.1. And having their converſations with Chriſt in heaven, to mortifie their members which are upon earth<note n="(b)" place="margin">Doe they mortifie their members, who ſeeke ſo much to pleaſe their eye. <hi>Joh. 15.19.</hi>
                     </note>: <hi>Col:</hi> 3.5. And thus plainely declaring by their words and actions, behaviour and apparrell, that they are not of this world, but are ſtrangers to it; in ſo doing, they ſhew forth the power of Chriſts reſurrection, drawing up their affections to himſelfe. As the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of mens hearts doth appeare (as it were written in their foreheads) in their vaine wanton faſhions<note n="(c)" place="margin">How doe theſe or their ſureties for them keepe their promiſe at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to forſake all the pomps and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this world? <hi>1 Theſ. 5 22.</hi>
                     </note>; ſo on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the grace of God in man doth appeare and ſhine in his Saints in their abſtaining upon pure Goſpell-grounds from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of pride, and vanity in apparrell, and cloathing themſelves with humility, as becomes the ſelfe-denying followers of Chriſt<note n="(d)" place="margin">Such ſelfe-denyall doth become thoſe who ſay they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> with Chriſt in Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſme.</note>. But as <hi>Paul</hi> complaines ſadly of ſome, who minded earthly things, that they were enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18. May wee not take up a light complaint of many now, who in adorning themſelves ſhew that they minde earthly things, by heaping on vaine ſuperfluities; are not ſuch enemies in this thing, or at leaſt, apparent non-conformiſts to the Croſſe of Chriſt? Great reaſon there is therefore that they who have otherwiſe learned Chriſt, dead and riſen, ſhould make it appeare, by putting off, or at leaſt forbearing to put on, ſuch things, which are not only unbecoming their profeſſion, but alſo are abuſed by moſt men, for an occaſion to the fleſh; and as they are commonly borne about, are appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently uſeleſſe to all, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.17, 20, 21, 22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2 Ground, or Reaſon.</note>As the firſt reaſon chiefely reſpects the croſſe of Chriſt, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecond in like manner, relates to his yoake, to which all beleevers owe ſubjection, and ought to manifeſt the ſame by a viſible uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall obedience to him, whom wee are bid to heare in all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.23. Who, as he hath by his owne mouth, ſpoken to his followers to deny themſelves, <hi>Math.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.34. So hath he by the mouth of his Apoſtles, in the holy Scriptures which he hath given to furniſh the man of God to every good worke,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44290:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
preſcribed profitable and precious directions for regulating the Saints practiſe in apparrelling themſelves. Theſe are either, firſt, more expreſſe and perticular, as to this one thing of adorning; as in 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.9. Where not onely is forbidden to beleeving women (that vanity they who have wherewith are too prone unto) to adorne themſelves with gold or pearles; but alſo the adorning themſelves with coſtly aray is there forbidden; that aray being there counted coſtly, which men crucified to this world,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.4. 2 Cor. 11.27, 28.</note> and often in neceſſities, and ſenſible of the wants of others, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> with others like minded accounted coſtly.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, There are directions which are more generall; of which I have here ſet downe ſome of the principall; as, <hi>Rom,</hi> 12.2. <hi>Be not conformed to this world.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.14. <hi>Faſhion not your ſelves according to the former luſts of your ignorance. Make no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the fleſh to fulfill the luſts thereof.</hi> Rom. 13.14. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, we are commanded <hi>to lay apart all filthineſſe, and ſuperfluity of naughtineſſe.</hi> Jam: 1.21. And in the 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 4.10. we are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>to be good Stewards of the manifold grace of God;</hi> which relates not only to ſpirituall gifts, but alſo to things of this life. Now with that ſpeciall rule before-going, let us take theſe generall rules, and well apply them<note n="(e)" place="margin">Thoſe Rules with many more ſuch are aſſented to in generall, but ſeldome applyed to any one thing in particular. <hi>1 Joh. 2.16. 3. Ground.</hi>
                     </note> to the particulars of evills forbidden, and dutyes enjoyned in thoſe Scriptures, and this doubt may ſoone be reſolved, Whether Saints are called to refraine from further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in ſuch vaine ſuperfluities, which the men of this world pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and put on, to <hi>ſatisfie the luſts of the fleſh, and the luſt of the eye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third ground is made good from the preſent apparent wants and ſtreights of divers poore precious Saints, that lack to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with things neceſſary; who by reaſon of ſickneſſe, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or want of Stock to manage their honeſt trades, are unable to provide for themſelves, and theirs ſo, that they may attend on God without diſtraction. Is not the ſupplying of their neede, the feeding and cloathing of Chriſt in his poore members, (for ſo he accounts what done to them, done to him, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.40.) to be preferr'd before providing ſuch needleſſe trimmings? Let the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-hearted ſober Chriſtian conſider it well. ſhould not Saints lay to heart theſe things, with a due reſpect to their receivings from Chriſt, and engagements to Chriſt, not forgetting the Law of their relation, as fellow-members with the meaneſt in that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy whereof Chriſt is head.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:44290:15"/>The third ground thus briefely laid downe, (with the caſe of the poore Saints unrelieved, ſtated truly, as it is) I leave this to the judgement of thoſe who are ſpirituall, and proceede to the fourth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">4. Ground.</note>The fourth ground is, That by ceaſing to caſt away their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance on ſuch ſuperfluities, Saints may be in a better capacity to adorne by their good works, the doctrine of God our Saviour; the credit whereof ought to be much dearer to us, then our lives; and how much then to be preferr'd before our needleſſe orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? How few of the men of the world are convinc't at this day by the Saints liberality to the poore, their ſeeking out the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and the fatherleſſe, the blind, and the lame, to relieve them in their diſtreſſe? How few, I ſay, are convinct on this account; <hi>viz.</hi> of ſuch good works done by profeſſors, that God is in them of a truth? and that the doctrine of grace they hold to, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is the true doctrine; Doe not many great profeſſors (on their part) leave the Goſpell naked, (without thoſe good works of mercy and bounty which ſhould adorne it) whilſt their fleſh is gorgeouſly arayed? Have not ſuch need to be put in remembrance of their duty, <hi>To honour the Lord with their ſubſtance, and with the firſt fruits of their encreaſe,</hi> Prov. 3.9. No ſooner doe they abound in wealth and riches, but ſuddenly they abound in coſtly ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (not in good works proportionable to their ability) thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of honouring the Lord, they honour themſelves with their ſubſtance, and inſtead of ſerving him, they even ſerve their luſts with the firſt fruits of all their encreaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">5. Ground.</note>A fifth reaſon for Saints reforming their apparrell, is taken from the manifold great temptations, and evills, Saints often fall into, to get that which is ſo lightly parted with in ſuperfluous orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Is it not eaſie to be ſeene, and ſadly to be lamented, that to provide and maintaine coſtly apparrell, ſtately houſes, rich houſe-furniture, delicious fare, and ſuch like things, according to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of this world; thoſe crying ſinnes of covetouſneſſe, deceite, injuſtice, with other like evills<note n="(f)" place="margin">What evill fire is that which muſt be fed with ſuch fewell?</note>, act their parts in ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of an high ſtraine, to the great diſhonour of the glorious name of God? And why is it that precious opportunities of aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling together, and viſiting one another, are ſo often neglected by the Saints? And oh, whence is it that there is ſo little looking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and preparing for the great day of Chriſts comming; the hearts of profeſſors being ſurfeited with the cares of this life, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44290:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that day ready to overtake them unawares; and they in danger to be found without their wedding garments? Is it not ſo with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or moſt, becauſe their endeavours are over-much laid out, and precious time (not to be redeemed with gold,) unprofitably ſpent<note n="(g)" place="margin">Is this to walke wiſely, redeeming the time, thus to ſpend it in vaine adornings?</note>, and waſted in providing, and putting on coſtly and curious apparrell; whereas to provide convenient garments, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch ornaments, and to procure other accommodations in, and about their houſes ſutable thereunto, ſo much time need not to be taken up, nor carefull thoughts<note n="(h)" place="margin">How many careful thoughts doe ſome take to provide and put on needleſſe deckings? how doe ſuch obey that word of Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 6.28. Take no thought for rayment? 6. Ground.</hi>
                     </note> (forbidden by Chriſt) laid out for themſelves, or their Children after them. Obſerve that word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6 28. <hi>Why take yee thought for rayment?</hi> and <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. <hi>After all theſe things doe the Gentiles ſeeke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſixth ground is taken from the glorious things promiſed to the people of God, who deale their bread to the hungry, and bring the poore out-caſts to their houſes. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58. 7, 8. &amp;c. <hi>viz. That their light ſhall riſe in obſcurity, their darkneſſe ſhall be as the noone day; they ſhall call, and the Lord will anſwer.</hi> Thoſe high enjoyments are here promiſed to a people who make another uſe of their outward ſubſtance, then to laviſh it on needleſſe orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the manner of ſome is. Unleſſe there be a reformation in this thing, what ſingular works of this kinde before-mentioned can be done by the Saints, which may be good Evidences, that God hath ſett them in the ready way to thoſe high attainments. They who waite for ſuch glorious things, and expect ſuch large meaſures of the Spirit, muſt learne to be good Stewards of the things of this life<note n="(i)" place="margin">They who waite for the Spirit muſt be content to part with all their fleſhly delights, and act as the wiſe Merchant man, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found one pearle of great price, ſold all and bought it. <hi>Mat. 13.45, 46</hi>
                     </note>. He that hath an eare, let him heare what Chriſt ſaith; <hi>If yee have not been faithfull in the unrighteous Mammon</hi> (the riches of this world) <hi>who will commit to your truſt the true riches? Hee that is unjuſt</hi> (or unfaithfull) <hi>in that which is leaſt, is unjuſt alſo in much,</hi> Luk. 16.10.11. The people whom God will uſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to raiſe up the foundations of many generations, to repaire breaches, and to reſtore pathes to dwell in, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 58.12. They ſhall not (as others have done) ſeeke great things for themſelves, but ſhall be a mercifull, holy, humble, ſelfe-denying people; as may appeare by comparing with the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, the five foregoing ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of that Chapter. And if God will doe ſuch great things by them, without doubt the Spirit of the Lord ſhall be early and abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly powred out upon them. Theſe things duely conſidered, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that thoſe precious promiſes, together with the Saints ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt expectation of ſuch great and glorious things to be fullfilled
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44290:16"/>
in this generation, doe lay a ſtrong engagement upon us, to ceaſe from our ſuperfluous ornaments, and all things elſe that hinder Saints from doing thoſe ſingular things before expreſſed, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.7, 8, 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">7. Ground.</note>Seventhly, The day and time we live in, calls to this refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. Is it not a time of trouble, a day of great rebuke, and grievous blaſphemies<note n="(i)" place="margin">See how <hi>Hezekiah</hi> though he were a king humbled himſelfe, &amp; put on ſackcloth and how the Lord takes notice of his ſo doing. <hi>Iſa. 37.1, 2.</hi>
                     </note>, wide breaches ſtill remaining among Gods people, glorious things brought to the birth, and no ſtrength to bring forth? And is not this a time for Saints rather to be rending, then decking their garments<note n="(k)" place="margin">Obſerve the practiſe of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoah</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leb,</hi> when the people ſpeke of making them a Captaine, and returning again into <hi>Aegypt, Num. 14.4.6.</hi> And ſee alſo the practiſe of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabas</hi> &amp; <hi>Saul. Acts 14.14.</hi>
                     </note>. Undoubtedly, the day calls to mourning, and humbling our ſelves, laying aſide our vaine ornaments? Is it a light thing to turne a deafe eare to Gods call by ſuch diſpenſations? And when he thus calls to a people to deny themſelves of their liberty<note n="(l)" place="margin">Are there not many ſuch profeſſors who minde their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty more then their duty?</note> in outward things, then to ſtretch to the utmoſt bounds thereof? <hi>Iſai.</hi> 22.12, 13. <hi>In that day</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>did the Lord of hoſts, call to weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and mourning, and girding with ſackcloth; and behold killing of ſheepe, and ſtaying of Oxen,</hi> &amp;c. And what followes? <hi>verſe</hi> the 14, <hi>And it was revealed in mine eares, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, This ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity ſhall not be purged from you till yee die.</hi> With this let the Reader compare diligently that noted word in <hi>Amos</hi> 6.5, 6, 7. Where thoſe are ſeverely threatned, who dranke wine in bowles, and forgatt the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph</hi>
                     <note n="(m)" place="margin">Let the women profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in <hi>London</hi> and elſewhere, who ſpend ſo little time in private praying and humbling themſelves, and ſo much in adorning themſelves with coſtly aray, and plaiting the hayre, let ſuch, I ſay, reade and marke well <hi>Iſaiah 3.</hi> From the ſixteenth forward. Can they chooſe but bluſh or rather tremble at that word?</note>. And can they eſcape much longer without correction, who doe ſuch things at this day? Doe not Saints put farre away the evill day, when they put on their vaine ornaments, and appeare with badges of pride, and not the marke of mourners upon them<note n="(n)" place="margin">Who that beholds the appartell of moſt profeſſors at this day, would take them to be ſuch as ſigh and cry for all the abomination of Gods people? Is not pride in apparrell one abomination? their partaking in it ſo apparently, plainly ſhews them without griefe for it.</note>? And ſhould it not be a Lamentation (that which is yet more unbecoming Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion) ſome glory in ſuch things, which are indeed their ſhame? He that feeles not the force of this reaſon taken from the hand of God upon us, and the many abominations and grievances before-mentioned, and hath no heart-bleedings becauſe of the reproach that is dayly caſt upon the name of God, and his people, &amp;c. let him examine himſelfe, whether hath he<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 28.4, 5.</note> due regard to the worke of the Lord at this day? And whether he be a reall mourner
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44290:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for <hi>Sion</hi>
                     <note n="(o)" place="margin">
                        <hi>See thoſe promiſes to them that mourne in</hi> Sion. Iſa. 61.2.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 66.10. 8 Ground.</note>? and one that preferres <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above his chiefe joy.</p>
                  <p>The eight is derived from that duty incumbent upon the Saints, <hi>to walke as lights amidst a crooked generation,</hi> Phil: 2.15. and as the Lords holy remnant whom he hath reſerved to witneſſe againſt the evills of the times. And who ſees not that pride in apparrell, is now a raigning ſin in this Land, even among profeſſors, who, in their adorning themſelves, differ little, or nothing, from the world, that wallowes in wickedneſſe, and vanity?<note place="margin">1 John 5.19.</note> That which aggravates this evill, and renders it more odious, and ſhould ſet Saints at the greater diſtance from it, and from all appearance thereof, is, that there is a troope of evills, as covetouſneſſe, defrauding, lying, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, grinding the faces of the poore, &amp;c. with many ſuch like ſinnes, which doe attend it. Can wee be zealous and jealous for the Lord of hoſts, and refraine from bearing a teſtimony of our diſlike of this abomination? And how can this be done, except we firſt begin at home, putting from us all appearance of that evill, which wee condemne in others? Gods people,<note place="margin">Rev. 18.4.</note> who are called to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> are ſtraitly charged not to partake of her ſinnes<note n="(p)" place="margin">Chriſts wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes doe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the beaſt not onely by word but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. Did not <hi>Noah</hi> by his practiſe in building an Arke condemne the old world?</note>; One reaſon is becauſe God will make uſe of them to declare againſt them. Now that the Saints may beare a full teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt this evill of pride in apparrell, which is one of the ſins of the times, and one of <hi>Babylons</hi> ſins, (as appeares. <hi>Revel:</hi> 18.12. and 15, 16 verſes.) It behoves them to cleere themſelves from it by a contrary practiſe<note n="(q)" place="margin">In ſuch away wee ought to man feſt our diſlike, ſo that he may runne that readeth it. 9 Ground.</note> to this corrupt generation in their proud manner of adorning themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Ninthly, The preſence of the Lord with his people, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them to this reformation, affords another ground<note n="(r)" place="margin">As God goes before his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to bring them out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> ſo to bring them off from her ſins.</note>: His hand (as they are perſwaded) having ſtrongly ſet it upon their hearts, in ſeverall Aſſemblies, ſolemnly waiting on him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme without delay, accounting that now God is purging away all the droſſe of <hi>Syon,</hi> he will not leave ſuch worldly ſuperfluities long remaining upon the garments of Saints. Its confeſt, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward impulſes, and perſwaſions of good men, are not alwayes good arguments to prove a matter: yet, when a praying people, ſuch as deſire to tremble at the Word, and labour to walke exactly, are unanimous in a perſwaſion or motion, which hath ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-grounds for it, as hath been alledged for this; Such an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in its place, well accompanied with other weighty reaſons, deſerves to be conſidered by ſuch as feare the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:44290:17"/>
                     <note place="margin">10 Ground.</note>The tenth and laſt ground is, becauſe of offence, which is taken by thoſe who ſigh and cry for all the abominations of profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors<note n="(s)" place="margin">God hath great regard to ſuch as ſigh and cry for all the evills of profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, though men make light and puffe at them. See &amp; conſider well, <hi>Ezek. 9.4, 5, 6.</hi>
                     </note>; They cannot but mourne to behold ſuch needleſſe coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deckings upon the apparrell of Saints. They alſo declare their conſcientious offence thereat. If <hi>Paul</hi> would not eate fleſh while the world was to ſtand rather then put a ſtumbling block in the way of his weake Brother, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 8.13. ſhould not Saints much rather refraine from thoſe needleſſe things, then give offence, and cauſe griefe to the tender hearts of thoſe for whom Chriſt dyed? And whereas it may be ſaid, ſome good men are offended at the leaving off ſuch ornaments<note n="(t)" place="margin">Wee may juſtly refraine from our liberty to avoid offence, but we may not neglect our duty to God for feare of offending good men.</note>; Is it from their goodneſſe? Is it not rather becauſe ſome private intereſt of their owne, or their friends, is thereby ſtruck at? If they be conſcientiouſly offended, the reaſons before-going may ſuffice to ſhew, that the offence is unjuſtly taken at thoſe, who on the grounds layd downe, ceaſe from putting on upon their garments ſuch ſuperfluous ornaments, and in conſcience towards God chooſe to walke in that way of reformation, whereon ſo cleere a light of truth ſhines.</p>
                  <p>Now, for as much as all reformation meets with oppoſition, it cannot well be expected, that this, which runs ſo contrary to the ſtreame of the common opinion and practiſe, and is ſo oppoſite to mens fleſhly luſts and intereſts, ſhould eaſily take place. I ſhall therefore proceed to conſider, and anſwer ſeverall Objections, which are, or may be made againſt the reformation pleaded for, and the grounds before laid downe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Object.</hi> Did not <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Rebeccah</hi> weare rich Jewells, and if ſo, why may not beleivers in theſe dayes, weare ſuch ornaments, if their abillity will extend to provide them?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, Wee finde not that there were at that day (as now there are) many poore Saints on every hand needing to be relieved.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Neither was proviſion made for their coſtly orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by ſuch notorious abominations, of covetouſneſſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, &amp;c. nor the pride of profeſſors, their pride in apparrell, growne up to that height, as that there needed then, as now there doth, ſuch a loud ſounding-teſtimony in word, and practiſe, to be borne againſt it.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Some things practiſed by <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> with as much approbation, as the wearing of Rings and Jewells<note n="(u)" place="margin">Did not their ear-rings ſoone become a ſnare unto them, elſe why did <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> take them away and hide them under an Oake when he reform'd his family, ſee <hi>Gen. 35.2, 3, 4.</hi> With this compare <hi>Exo. 32.2, 3, 4.</hi> See what uſe the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> made of their golden ear-rings. And did not golde eare-rings prove a ſnare to <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and his houſe, <hi>Judg. 8.26, 27.</hi>
                     </note> by <hi>Sarah,</hi> and <hi>Rebeccah,</hi> it becomes not Saints to practiſe: Had not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44290:17"/>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> his Concubines, and children by them? <hi>Gen:</hi> 25.6. And did not <hi>David</hi> take unto him many wives and Concubines? 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 5.13. Would not Saints bluſh to be found walking in their ſteps in theſe things now?</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, In thoſe dayes of ignorance, in the infancy of the Church, God dealt with his people as Parents doe with their little Children, who give them ſuch things as are taking to the eye, to win upon their affections; and lay ſuch commands upon them, as are ſutable to their tender age, and preſent capacity. So did God give goodly outward gifts, and ornaments to his people of old under the Law. And as he hath at ſundry times, and in ſundry wayes, ſo alſo by ſeverall degrees, diſcovered his will to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, according to that ability he hath given them to beare. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it will not follow, becauſe God did at firſt tolerate the wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch ornaments, that therefore now he calls not his to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny themſelves in theſe things. The preſident of ſome wearing ſuch ornaments then, makes not ſo much for that practiſe, as thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Goſpel-precepts laid downe in the ſecond ground, with thoſe other arguments accompanying make againſt it now.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Object.</hi> This is for the honour of Chriſt, that his ſervants and followers put on ſuch ornaments, ſeeing thereby they make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare they ſerve a good Maſter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is for the honour of Chriſt our head, and Lord, to have his members and followers conformable to him<note n="(w)" place="margin">It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the diſciple that he be as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and the ſervant as his Lord.</note>, even to Chriſt crucified, as were the Miniſters of Chriſt, and his deſpiſed followers in the primitive times. As for thoſe who judge of the condition of the ſervants of Chriſt, either of their happineſſe or miſery, with reſpect to their outward ſtate, and accommodations, what would ſuch have thought of Chriſt, had they ſeene him borne in a manger, and hanged on a tree? The miſtaken world, which (as <hi>John</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2.) <hi>knoweth not the Saints,</hi> judging af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the wiſdome of this world by ſuch falſe rules, may, and ſhall, ſtumble at the Saints, as they did at Chriſt, who were offended at him, and ſaid, <hi>Is not this the Carpenters ſonne?</hi> It is the glory of the members to be like their head, the followers to be like their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. The legall worſhip, Temple, and worſhippers, had indeed rich adornings belonging to them, which was to the honour of God in that day, under that diſpenſation; But the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-glory is inward, in the Spirit, in the hidden man of the heart. The typicall Temple was adorned with Gold and Silver, but the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44290:18"/>
true Temple ſpoken of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. is adorned within with that which is not corruptible, and outwardly with ſuch ſelfe-denyall and good workes before men as doe become the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Object.</hi> Some object, this would be to expoſe our ſelves to ſcorne, and to make our ſelves ridiculous in the eyes of men, if wee ſhould put off our ornaments, and walke in that way which here ſeemes to be preſcribed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, Such extremities are not here pleaded for, as may occaſion ſuch contempt to be caſt upon you. Who will laugh at you, for forbearing to put on upon good and convenient gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſuch ſuperfluous trimming, as hath no ſhew of uſe? Is it not uſuall with civill people to commend going plaine, as they call it, and to condemne profeſſors for their pride in apparrell? As for holy mortified perſons, they are more exerciſed in ſighing for all the abominations of the times, then that they ſhould be found to contemne any man upon ſuch an account. Some light profeſſors there are, who neither lay to heart their owne, nor others ſinnes, but like <hi>Dives,</hi> they cloath themſelves ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and fare deliciouſly every day<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Luk. 16.19.23, 24, 25, 28.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This deſcription of <hi>Dives</hi> his fine cloathing and ſumptuous fare, &amp;c. and withall his fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full end, may ſerve for a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Caution to ſome who even tread in his ſteps.</p>
                        <p>They who keepe to the word may expect to be for ſignes &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even among profeſſors.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>a. 8.16, 17, 18.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </note>, ſuch (being too much accuſtomed to vaine laughter) may laugh in the face at ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, whilſt inwardly they have indignation againſt it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it witneſſeth againſt their vaine practiſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The ſervants and followers of Chriſt ought not to thinke it ſtrange if they be counted for ſignes and wonders, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is no other then what was propheſied before-hand in the Scriptures, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.18. <hi>Zach:</hi> 3.8. How could ſuch lay downe their lives for the truths of Chriſt, who cannot beare to be laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at for righteouſneſſe-ſake? whilſt the glory of God is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by their endeavours for ſuch a reformation, whereof they ſee there is at this day among the Saints ſo great a neede.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Object.</hi> God hath promiſed that his people ſhall poſſeſſe the riches of the Gentiles, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 60.9.17. and that they ſhall have plenty of Gold, and Silver, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.6. If ſo, and God hath already begun to ſubdue our enemies, ſo that they ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and come with preſents to us; why then, may we not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, and put on coſtly jewells, and ornaments? What better uſe can wee make of the riches wee poſſeſſe?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, That thoſe Prophecies doe agree with what is written in the booke of <hi>Revelation</hi> concerning new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and have relation to the ſame glorious ſtate of the Church, may evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44290:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
appeare by comparing the ſixtieth Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> with the 21 of <hi>Revelation.</hi> Its true indeed, the Kings ſhall bring their glory into it, &amp;c. but that the Saints are not yet come to that new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-ſtate, is ſufficiently manifeſt from that ſorrow, and ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the many ſad complaints of Gods people as at this day; all which, as alſo the preſent poverty and ſuffering, of many Saints, are inconſiſtent with their glorious priviledges in the New <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; for there ſhall be no ſorrow, nor crying,</hi> Revel: 21.4. If it be granted, that ſuch ornaments ſhall be worne by Saints in their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant ſtate then, it will not therefore follow, that they may put them on in their militant ſtate now, whilſt the dayes of their mourning are not ended, and whilſt the bridegroome is not with them<note n="(y)" place="margin">The children of the bride-chamber cannot but mourne whilſt the bride-groome is not with them.</note>.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Saints ought to be ſo afflicted in and for the afflictions one of another, that as fellow-members of one body; <hi>If one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſuffer</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>all ſuffer with it,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.26. Upon this account, how deeply ought we to be affected with the lamentable miſeries of Gods people in many Lands, who groane dayly under grievous ſufferings by perſecution, reproach, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and all manner of oppreſſion? Are any of us ſet at liberty from ſuch bondage, ought we not yet, to conſider our ſelves in the ſame body with them? and be in bonds (in reſpect of a ſympathy and fellow-feeling of their grievances) as if we were bound with them? <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.3. and can we be thus affected, and yet plead for, and put on coſtly aray, and rich ornaments (as the manner of ſome is, who lay not theſe things to heart) as if all were well<note n="(z)" place="margin">Are not ſuch like <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi> of whom its ſaid when <hi>Soſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> was bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten he cared for none of theſe things.</note>, and nothing aileth us? I ſhall not here meddle with that queſtion, What times to come may allow of? onely let mee allude to the words of <hi>Haggai</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Hag.</hi> 3. <hi>Is this a time for you, O yee, to dwell in your ceiled houſes?</hi> ſo, is this a time for Saints to be decking themſelves with coſtly ornaments, whilſt ſo many of their brethren abroad are wounded, and lye as it were bleeding even to death<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mark how <hi>Moſes</hi> reproves the children of <hi>Gad</hi> and of <hi>Reuben</hi> when they would ſit downe before their brethren were put into their poſſeſſion. <hi>Shall your brethren goe to warre, and ſhall yee ſit here?</hi> Numb. <hi>32.6.</hi>
                     </note>? Might it not rather become a true hearted <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> with a tender eye to theſe things, to ſay with <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> 2 Sam: 11.11. <hi>The Ark, and Iſrael, and Judah, remaine in tents, and the ſervants of the Lord are encamped in the open field,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall I then goe into mine houſe, to eate, and drinke?</hi> &amp;c. May not this his ſaying ſhame many profeſſors now, who abate nothing of their ſuperfluities upon the account of all the wants, ſorrowes, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of the people of God<note n="(b)" place="margin">As thoſe who are not grieved for the afflictions of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> give the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to drinke wine in bowles, &amp;c. <hi>Amos 3.</hi> So on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary they who are grieved for <hi>Joſephs</hi> afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are led to deny themſelves to ſuch things.</note>, and all that reproach which is caſt upon the glorious name and cauſe of God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:44290:19"/>Thirdly, Hath God bleſt his people in this Nation with the firſt-fruits of thoſe promiſes? ſhould they firſt ſerve and adorne themſelves, and not rather honour the Lord, and adorne his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, by relieving the poore Saints, and others, with the firſt-fruits of all their encreaſe<note n="(c)" place="margin">God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of old that they ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay the firſt fruits of all their encreaſe. <hi>Exod. 22.29.</hi> With which compare that word in <hi>Ezek. 20.41.</hi> Which relates to latter or laſt dayes.</note>? As for the late warre (wherein the cauſe of Chriſt and his Saints was pleaded with ſuch great reſolution and wonderfull ſucceſſe) was it not at firſt promoted by the free offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the godly, and well-affected people, who brought in their money, plate, and jewells, and kept not backe their lives, when they were cal'd for<note n="(d)" place="margin">Did not the people as in the dayes of old offer themſelves and their's willingly to the worke of the Lord, aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with their lives in their hands, that the cauſe was the Lords. The peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple went out as they were cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led thereunto, to helpe the Lord againſt the mighty.</note>? Let it be conſidered whether the rich ſpoyles gotten by ſuch a warre ſhould not have been brought into a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique treaſury, to be faithfully diſpoſed of for the benefit of the cauſe and people of God<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Joſhua 6.18, 19.</hi> the gold and ſilver taken from the enemy, converted to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ends and uſe, became a curſe and a trouble to the Campe.</note>; the inſtruments imployed taking to themſelves food and raiment convenient for them, not laying up for themſelves, nor laying out for their luſts? How well would ſuch a courſe agree with that remarkeable word, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 23.18. <hi>The merchandiſe of Tyre</hi> (which in reſpect of her fornication with the Nations doth fitly reſemble myſticall <hi>Babylon) and her hire ſhall be holineſſe to the Lord; it ſhall neither be treaſured, nor laid up, but it ſhall be for them that dwell before the Lord, to eate ſufficiently, and for durable Cloathing</hi>
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">Doe not ſome to maintaine gay cloating, binde heavy burdens on the backs of Saints?</note>? And if theſe things ought to have been done, and are not, but that which is contrary to them, may wee not conclude, that the coſtly apparrell, and the great treaſures of many who are inriched by the late warres, (conſidering the ſtate of affaires civill and ſpirituall in theſe nations<note n="(g)" place="margin">Faſting and prayer are commendable things, but the breaking off hard yoakes is that which is more acceptable to God, <hi>Iſa. 58.5, 6.</hi>
                     </note>, and the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thouſands of Saints at this day in the world) are more like <hi>Achans</hi> golden wedge, &amp; <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> garment<note n="(h)" place="margin">Are there not ſome <hi>Achans</hi> to be diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and puniſht before the Lord will give his preſence in the Campe? Doe not his late diſpenſations ſpeake with a voice like that, <hi>Joſh. 7.13. There is an accurſed thing in the midſt of thee O Iſrael, thou canſt not ſtand before thine enemies, untill &amp;c.</hi> Reade the <hi>6</hi> of <hi>Joſh, 18, 19.</hi> and the 7th Chapter throughout, and compare diligently the things that have been, with the things that are, and take heed of being taken with goodly <hi>Babyloloniſh</hi> garments, gotten by the ſpoyles of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>Joſh. 7.21.</hi>
                     </note>, then like the great riches Saints ſhall poſſeſſe, and the golden ornaments (as is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) they ſhall put on, in the day of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> perfect proſperity?</p>
                  <p n="5">5 <hi>Object.</hi> Others ſay we feare leaſt by forbearing to put on ſuch ornaments, wee ſhould give occaſion to the world to charge us with covetouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:44290:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the exerciſe of your liberality in relieving the poore Saints, by entertaining ſtrangers, and ſuch like workes, ſuch cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures may eaſily be prevented<note n="(i)" place="margin">Whether they who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the keeping of their ſoules to God in well-doing, ought in like manner to commit the keeping of their good names to him.</note>. If any forbeare the wearing of coſtly aray, in deſigne to reſerve the gaine thereby for their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, they are juſtly ſerv'd, if that reproach fall upon them. Yet all this makes nothing againſt a conſcientious reformation in apparrell, which is a ſpeciall helpe againſt covetouſneſſe, an evill practiſed by moſt men to uphold their pride. Wherefore let them both fall together, and this objection will be gone.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 <hi>Object.</hi> What ſay ſome? wee feare leaſt by leaving off our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous ornaments, wee ſhould bring our ſelves into danger of being numbred with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſeeing they are obſerved to ſpeake much againſt pride in apparrell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, Firſt, May wee not as well on the ſame ground ceaſe to declare againſt falſe worſhip, and to ſpeake of the Spirit, becauſe they who are called <hi>Quakers</hi> doe ſuch things, and others who ſhall ſo doe are like to be ſo accounted?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Some men doe good things on evill grounds, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote bad deſignes; wee may not therefore refuſe to doe the ſame things on good and righteous grounds.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,<note n="(i)" place="margin">How few doe ſhew Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-faith by their obedience to that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, which bids them to rejoyce and leape for joy, when men ſhall reproach them for his ſake. <hi>Luk. 6.22, 23.</hi>
                     </note> If this thing be of God (as hath been before ſhewed at large) we ought not to be diſcouraged therein on any ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.7. But herein rather to rejoyce <hi>(k),</hi> if we be counted worthy to ſuffer that, or any other ſhame for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſake; for Chriſt hath pronounced ſuch ſufferers greatly bleſſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10, 11, 12. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.22, 23.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Conſider whether this peoples ſtanding up to plead for the Spirit; as alſo for reforming in habit, and for ſome other good things, at this time, may not have in it a deſigne of Satan, to bring up an evill report upon thoſe good things, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that practiſe, and ſeeke to promote them<note n="(l)" place="margin">Satan he doth it in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, but God in juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth lay ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling blocks before men. <hi>Jer. 6.21. Luk. 2.34. Iſa. 8.14. 1 Pet. 2.7.</hi>
                     </note>? May wee not, I ſay, looke at this as a ſtumbling blocke caſt in the way to hinder this good worke by the Enemy of man, who leaves no way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attempted to ſtirre up the minds of men to prejudice againſt the truth?</p>
                  <p n="7">7 <hi>Object.</hi> The great cry of many is ſomewhat like to that of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius,</hi> Act. 19.25. By this craft we have our wealth, <hi>viz.</hi> many rich trades by Sea and Land, whereby many families are maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, are upheld by the wearing of coſtly ornaments on apparrell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, Obſerve that this objection is agreeable to that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44290:20"/>
prophecy, <hi>Rev:</hi> 18. which deſcribes the dolefull complaint of the Merchants of the earth at <hi>Babylons</hi> fall, when her pride and pompe is brought downe, as we reade, verſ. 18. <hi>They caſt duſt on their heads, and cry, Alas! Alas! that great City! wherein were made rich, all that had Ships in the Sea, by reaſon of her coſtlineſſe</hi>
                     <note n="(m)" place="margin">Are there not divers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings among the people of <hi>England</hi> at the removing of Popiſh ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe the trade was maintained by coſtly proviſions for them.</note>. Such complaints becomes not the ſons of <hi>Sion,</hi> who have their converſation in Heaven. They are bidden to rejoyce at her fall, even then when thoſe Merchants mourne: ſee <hi>Revel:</hi> 18.20.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, As for the families maintained by ſuch trades, are they rich? or are they poore? If rich, are the Saints bound to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch? who hath required this at their hands? If poore, and if the good of the poore and their families be the mark aym'd at in ſuch wearings, were it not much better that what they have to lay out in ſuch ſuperfluities, might be given immediately into the hands of the diligent poore? or ſuch as through age, or other infirmity of body, and unable to work? If in buying ſuch things at the ſhops, men act conſcientiouſly for ſupport of the poore; doe they act wiſely, to let the rich ſhop-keeper gaine ſo much by them<note n="(n)" place="margin">By that time the gaines have paſſed through the ſhop-keepers hands, little is that which is left for the poore.</note>, who oft proves a bad Steward of their bounty, and an hard task-maſter to the poore that work for him? The Scripture abounds with many great and precious promiſes to him, who from a right principle within, gives liberally to the poore, as, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53.7, 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c. Luk.</hi> 14.13, 14. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.2, 3. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.41. <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. 10th. But what one word of them, or what other promiſe can a man war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably apply to himſelfe in buying ſuch trimmings? Let the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant profeſſors conſider it well, and aske their experience, Will it give them a cleere teſtimony of Gods promiſe or preſence with them in ſo doing? but in giving to the poore, that duty ſo oft commanded and commended to us by the Lord, many humble and mercifull men can ſay they have mett with many good words of promiſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.10.</note> more ſweete then honey, and dearer then thouſands of gold. <hi>Hee that pitieth the poore</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) lendeth to the Lord, and that which he hath given will he pay him againe,</hi> Prov. 19.17. But can ſuch who lay out their money at the ſhops in coſtly ornaments, account that in ſo doing they lend unto the Lord? and that God will pay it them again? ſo that they who thus act, ſhew thmſelves in this matter neither wiſe for the poore, nor for themſelves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:44290:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thirdly, As for ſuch as are poor in Churches, who are imployed in making Lace, and ſuch like Ornaments, If God enlarge the hearts of the rich Members to ſtudy to do ſome ſingular works of mercy, cauſing them in order thereunto, to ceaſe from their coſtly ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in houſe-furniture, apparell and delicious fare, and from ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great things for themſelves, and theirs, they may (without doubt) ſet their poor fellow-members on work, in providing things honeſt for neceſſary uſes, whereby they may bee more profitable to their Generation, and ſpend their dayes on earth with more ſatisfaction, and to a better account, than in making, and providing ſuch vain things, which tend to little profit, but for the moſt part meerly ſerve the luſts and humours of proud men. Let ours alſo (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.14) <hi>Learn to maintain good works</hi> (ſome read ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Trades) for neceſſary uſes, that they bee not unfruitfull. Might not the poor Saints, if the rich were bleſt with an heart to deviſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall things, bee ſet on work, in making coates (with <hi>Dorcas, Act.</hi> 9.39.) and other linnen and woollen Garments for poor wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and for the Fatherleſſe? and would not this bee a praiſe-worthy work, and that which would give occaſion to all behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to glorify God? ſo that if wee reſpect the glory of God, the good of the Poor, and our own Comfort, the way that is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to go to the ſhops, and upon the account of maintaining Trade, to lay out their mony in needleſſe Laces, Points, and Ribbands to put them on upon good Cloathes, which are convenient, and may well become us without them, this way I ſay is not the beſt, and moſt excellent.</p>
                  <p>Obj. 8 <hi>Some great Profeſſors are ready to object, we may provide and put on ſuperfluous Ornaments, and yet reſerve enough to beſtow on the Poor, ſeeing the number of them whom wee are called to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve is but ſmall, and moſt of them can make a ſhift to live with little help.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, Such ought to know and conſider, that of thoſe whom God hath bleſt with a liberall portion of outward things, hee expects and requires a proportionable excerciſe of liberality, for to whom much is given, of the ſame much ſhall bee required,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Obſerve how the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows two mites are valued above the great gifts of the rich, Mark. 12.43, 44. 1 Pet 1.14, 15.</note> 
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.29. And yet the rich (even in ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of Saints) count they do well, and enough, if they give to the relief of the poor double what other mean men do, two ſhillings to their one; whereas (did they diſpenſe their gift accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their ability) they would give fifty for others one. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44290:21"/>
who are rich in this world, are required to bee rich in good works, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 6.17.18. And if any man miniſter let him do it as of the ability which God giveth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Do ſuch, in relieving the poor, walk by that rule, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.11. Thou ſhalt open thine hand wide unto thy brother, to thy poor, and to thy needy in the land? and in the verſe before, Thou ſhalt ſurely give him, and ſhalt not bee grieved; and again in the 14. verſe, Thou ſhalt furniſh him liberally out of that wherewith the Lord thy God hath bleſſed thee. But on the contrary, is it not ordinary with ſome that are Rich, to count it enough to keep their Brethren from periſhing? How few walk up to that Golden Rule, Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf? hee that ſo loves his Neighbour, ſeeks to make his life in ſome meaſure comfortable as bee doth his own, and in ſo doing (though not for ſo doing in way of deſert) more joy is to bee found, than in the greateſt worldly glory, which when men have purchaſed with much expence, procures them little comfort here, and will afford them leſſe in the day of Chriſt. May not many who ſo laviſh out their Gold and Silver on their ſumptuous cloathing, juſtly fear leſt they fall under that heavy charge in the day of Chriſt; <hi>I was naked, and yee cloathed mee not, hungry, and yee fed me not, Mat.</hi> 25.42.43. Such as now wear coſtly apparell on the back, with great bunches of Ribbands on the belly (as the manner of ſome is) will they not then bluſh, and bee aſhamed when they ſhall bee called to look back and ſee how they have uſed their talents, and be required to give up their account to<note n="(p)" place="margin">Doe not the brave gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants put that great day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts far off?</note> God?</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, They know few in want. If they were not willingly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, they might ſoon be informed of many objects of pity, who call for large bounty, and bowells to relieve them in their preſent wants and<note n="(q)" place="margin">Such give little encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to others to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them with their wants.</note> ſtreights. The time is neer, wherein that word ſhall bee fullfilled. <hi>Eſay</hi> 32.5. The vile perſon (ſuch an one as firſt ſerveth his Luſts, and then throws a little of the overplus to the Poor) ſhall bee no more counted liberal, nor the Churl (who poſſibly will do ſomething for the poor by much entreaty) ſhall no more bee ſaid to bee bountifull, but the liberal man ſhall bee known by that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recter, in the 18. verſe, by deviſing liberall things, and mark what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, by liberal things ſhall hee ſtand. To ſeek out the Poor and needy, the hungry and the naked to feed and cloath them, and to avoid all unneceſſary expence, that he may be the better able to do ſuch works, this ſpeaks a man liberal indeed, thus to deviſe liberal things.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44290:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And hee that doth thus (providing things honeſt and needful for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and for his family) as hee is likely to find no lack, ſo to have little, or nothing over, wherewith to provide coſtly ſuperfluities. For concluſion of the anſwer of this objection,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.15.</note> let mee without offence propoſe to ſome Saints in Churches, whether do they remember their Brethren in other Congregations beſides their own, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer adverſity, as being in the ſame body of Chriſt with them, and do they make it appear by caring naturally for them, and extending re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief to them, according to examples of the primitive Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2, 3. compared with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1, 2, 3. &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.29, 30.</p>
                  <p>Object. 9. <hi>It is enough for us to avoid ſome extream vain faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to conform in our apparrel to other civil people of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This ſaying ſuites well with the Laodiocans of our times, who are much taken with the friendſhip of this world, but to ſuch I ſhal uſe the words of the Prophet, <hi>Ariſe, depart yee, this is not your reſt, for it is polluted:</hi> Hath not Pride infected all degrees, high, and low, from the greateſt maſters to the meaneſt of Servants? Not to ſpeak of the Pride and pomp of ſome men, and how it is ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Do wee not ſee, that even thoſe who get their living hardly, by their daily labour, inſtead of laying up againſt the time of age or ſickneſſe, lightly lay out what with labour they get, on vain and coſtly<note n="(r)" place="margin">Such trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings as are uſed by poore ſervants are oft times more coſtly to them then other rich adornings worne by men of eſtates.</note> ſuperfluities? And what do they alledge, but that its ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for others as mean as themſelves ſo to do? But let Saints remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that command of God, Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to do evil, <hi>Exo.</hi> 23.2. and the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. where wee are commanded to bee non conformiſts to this World, and withal obſerve his earneſt exhortation to the beleeving Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, not to walk as other Gentiles, in the vanitie of their mind, &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.17. to the 23. verſe, for further anſwer ſee the 8 ground.</p>
                  <p>Object. 10. <hi>Some who ſeem to bee high-flown in knowledge and contemplation, object againſt this Reformation, that this is a ſmall matter, and ſo they puff at it, and are offended as</hi> Naaman <hi>the</hi> Syrian, <hi>when the Prophet bid him do a ſmall thing,</hi> 2 King 5.11.13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, Doth God call for it? be it granted that the thing is but ſmall, in compariſon of ſome weighty matters, ſo much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought it to bee done by the Saints without gainſaying. But ſo ſmall a thing as it is, weightier matters are highly concerned in it; for (beſides the clear tendency of this Reformation, to promote many
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44290:22"/>
ſingular good works, which would adorn the Saints profeſſion, and turn for a teſtimony to them, that God hath ſet them in the way of thoſe choice and high enjoyments ſpoken of in the ſixth ground) it lays ſiedge to thoſe mighty ſinnes, viz. Covetouſneſſe, Oppreſſion, Extortion, Injuſtice, Fraudulent dealing, with many other like evills, which are practiſed mainly to maintain a worldly gallantry in coſtly apparell, and ſuch like ſuperfluities.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, To allow our ſelves in any evill, though but a ſmall one, is no ſmall evill but a great one, ſuch as makes a deep wound in a tender Conſcience, and prepares the way to the worſt of evills,<note n="(s)" place="margin">See the danger of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wilfully Heb. 10.25, 26 27, 28 and take heede of the leaſt ſlip that leades to it.</note> Have not theſe times abounded with ſad examples of ſome, who at firſt ſlighting ſome leſſer commands of the Goſpell, and giving place to ſinne by little and little, have at length become deſpiſers of the Ordinances of Chriſt, and have ſet light by Chriſt himſelf, and his precious blood, turning the grace of God into wantonneſſe; abuſing Goſpell liberty for an occaſion to the fleſh, even unto groſſe Licenciouſneſſe? Wherefore the rather ought Saints to bee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in all things, and to avoid ſuch arguing in defence of ſmall ſinnes,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.13 Eph. 5.15 1 Theſ. 5.22</note> ſeeing it proves oft times a ſad beginning that leads to a fearful end. And now in as much as God is turning his hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his People, to purge away all their droſſe, according to his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed word, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 1.25. Wee ought to ſee his hand upon us, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to ſubmit thereunto, as workers with him in the ſtrength of his grace,<note place="margin">Iſai. 4.4, 5.</note> to clenſe our ſelves from all filthineſſe of fleſh and ſpirit, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting holineſſe in the fear of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 34, laſt. 3 Mal. 2, 3. Iſai. 33.15</note>The bright beams of that light, which is now riſing on the Saints, will diſcover the leaſt motes of evil remaining in them, and that fire which is in <hi>Sion</hi> wil leave no ſtubble remaining. Theſe things duly conſidered, this objection is no juſt exception againſt the reformation aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>Object. 11. <hi>Some affirm with no ſmall confidence, that their hearts are dead to things below, they take no pride or pleaſure in their coſtly apparel, though it be made, and put on after the newest faſhion, therefore they may, and can without ſcruple wear ſuch things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, If your hearts are dead indeed to them, the offence that is given to many tender hearts by ſuch adornings, were there no other ground, may the more eaſily prevail with you to part with them.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Some who have thought thus of themſelves, upon a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44290:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſleight ſearch, upon further and more ſtrict inquiry, have not found their hearts free from the infection of pride in apparel, which where it is in moſt Profeſſors, may be diſcerned by others, at leaſt by themſelves (upon a cloſe ſearch) in theſe two things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Their clayming, or at leaſt expecting ſome more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary reſpect ſuitable to their habit; yea, and if they come into the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of Saints, they look to be preferred to the beſt places, and that it ſhould be ſaid or done to them according to that word in <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.2. <hi>If there come into your aſſemblies a man with a gold ring, and goodly apparel, and there come in alſo a poor man in vile rayment, you have reſpect to him that weareth the gay cloathing, and ſay to him, Sir, ſit thou here in a good place,</hi>
                     <note n="(t)" place="margin">Is there not ſome ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality to bee ſeen in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of Saints at this day?</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Their ſtrange carriage to their poor brethren; How do ſuch bluſh &amp; are aſhamed to walk the ſtreets with their poor brethren in mean rayment?<note n="(u)" place="margin">Is not this denial of Chriſt in his poor members like that of Peter when he ſaid in the high Prieſts hall, I know not the man?</note> Do they not ſhun their company in open places of concourſe, and ſometimes ſeem to diſ-own them? Are they not aſhamed to call them (or be called by them) brethren <hi rend="sup">v</hi>? And why are they thus aſhamed to own Chriſt in his poor members? It ſtands not with their honor to be ſeen with them, or at leaſt to be familiar with them<note n="(w)" place="margin">Yet is not Chriſt aſhamed to call them brethren. Heb. 2.11.</note>. This becomes not thoſe of their rank that wear ſuch coſtly rich cloathing. And if theſe things be ſo, beware leſt your hearts deceive you in this matter, but let that be taken away, which is ſuch a ſnare, and a ſtumbling-block to Saints.</p>
                  <p>Obj ct. 12. <hi>Now may ſome ſay, we find our ſelves upon the conſideration of the whole matter, ſo far informed, that we know where to begin; we are convinced of ſome of our adornings, that they are vain, fooliſh, and offenſive, unbecoming Saints, but wee know not where to end, or what bounds to ſet to this reformation. Moreover we fear that hot contentions may ariſe among Saints about this matter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> In following our light,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> we ought not to be of doubtful mind, but in this, as in other things, whereto wee have attained, wee ought to walk, waiting for further light in the improvement of the meaſure received. In reforming Religion from Popery and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, &amp;c. who could at firſt ſet, or who can yet ſet the bounds to that reformation begun, ſo as to declare in every particular, whereto it will grow, ſo as to ſay hitherto ſhall it proceed, and no farther? or who could, or can yet reſolve all the doubts and queſtions that have riſen concerning that matter? nor was that or any other reformation that I could yet hear of, brought forth without ſome
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44290:23"/>
contention<note n="(x)" place="margin">What birth is there that comes without travel.</note>; but if upon ſuch accounts any perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſhould (notwithſtanding their being convinced of the need there was of a reformation) have withſtood the work, or refuſed to enter upon it, they might bee juſtly judged for their oppoſition, or neglect; It being Gods ordinary way when hee ſets his people upon a work at firſt, after conviction, to give them a meaſure of light accompanied with zeal and confidence, ſerving for an entrance, and after that, to come in with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of light for the carrying on the work begun, thus leading his people, as by ſtep and ſtep. Theſe things are plain, and the application may eaſily bee made to the matter in hand.</p>
                  <p>As for the contention that may ariſe, Is it not the ordinary lot of the work of Reformation, and every part or peece thereof to paſſe thorow ſuch fire, that both it and thoſe who ſtand for it, may bee tryed? And ſuch as hate to bee reformed (though they take Law and Goſpel in their mouth) may bee diſcovered? But let men take heed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they contend not againſt any part of Gods work<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſa. 50, 16 2 Cor. 3, 18 wee can doe nothing againſt the truth but for the truth this becomes Saints thus to ſay and do Matt. 3, 15.</note>, or that they bee not found Newters when God cals to ſide with him in any part of righteouſneſſe, conſidering the words of our bleſſed Lord, <hi>Hee that is not with mee is againſt mee, and hee that gathereth not with mee ſcattereth abroad, Mat.</hi> 12.30. As for remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any other obſtruction that may lye in the way to hinder this Reformation, I referre the Godly Reader to a diligent peruſall of the ground laid down, with the anſwers given to the ſeveral objections before mentioned.</p>
                  <p>Query. <hi>Here it may bee queſtioned by ſome, who are or may bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied touching the Reformation contended for,</hi> viz. <hi>Whether being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd that Saints ought not to put on ſuch ſuperfluous trimmings as are before ſpoken againſt: Shall wee ſtraightway take off ſuch things if now wee have them on? What good way come to us, or others, by ſo doing?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Can you, being convinc'd in the thing, keep them on with comfort? Conſidering</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That in continuing them on, by example (which is a thing many look at in ſuch matters) you uphold the evill, and promote it in others, who are incouraged by beholding your vain adorning, to procure and put on the like.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, You can not well uſe tongue or pen to oppoſe ſuch ſuperfluous Ornaments on others, ſeeing they remain on your own Apparel. Will not every man bee ready to ſay, <hi>Pluck out
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44290:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
firſt the beam which is in your own eye?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, You may never live to wear out the cloathes you put on, ſo that if you ſhould think then to reform, when you have done with them, and not before, you may never live to have the honour to do God that ſervice to bear your teſtimony againſt that evill. Remember the wiſe mans words, Ecceſiaſt. 9.10. <hi>Whatſoever thine hand findeth to do, do it with thy might, for there is no work nor device, nor wiſdome, nor knowledge in the grave, whither thou goeſt.</hi> If therefore you have light leading you to bear your teſtimony in word and practice againſt ſuch ſuperfluities, <hi>Walk in the light, whilſt you have the light,</hi> Joh. 12.36.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Although the putting off ſuch things ſeems to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent no preſent outward advantage to any man, yet inaſmuch as it puts a man into the better capacity to help forward a generall Reformation among Gods people, and ſeeing the great good which may bee expected to come thereby, will, to the great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of publick-ſpirited Chriſtians, ſoon countervail the parting with thoſe things, (which are no gain, but rather loſſe to them that wear them) therefore let them bee parted with, and no longer retained by Saints.<note place="margin">The Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it is expedient there ſhould bee ſome Reformation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Saints in their Apparel, in reſpect of ſome extravagancies and vain ſuperfluities, moſt, or all good men acknowledge. As for the way that is preſented to the Saints in this Diſcourſe, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not but it may bee liable to exceptions in ſome caſes, and ſo are many or moſt generall Rules in the Scriptures of<note n="(z)" place="margin">That great Command and for doing no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of work on the Sabbath, did admit of exceptions in ſome caſes, as appears Matth. 12. the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the chapter. 2 Pet, 2.12.</note> Truth. If they who are friends to this work, diſlike this eſſay, or rough draught, let them bring forth their poliſhed Endeavours on this Subject. In the mean time, this I ſay to all that fear the Lord, who upon the reading hereof ſhall remain diſ-ſatisfyed in this matter: Take heed that yee ſpeak not evill of the things yee know not, or have not conſidered, but ſeriouſly weigh, as in the ſight of God, and in his holy fear, the things laid down in this Diſcourſe, not forgetting or neglecting to ſeek the Lord herein, remembring the words of wiſdom, Prov. 28.5. <hi>They that ſeek the Lord underſtand all things.</hi> I ſhall ſhut up all with the words of <hi>Gamaliel</hi> to the Jews. <hi>If this counſell or work bee of men,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 5.</note> 
                     <hi>it will come to nought, but if it bee of God, yee cannot overthrow it, leſt happily yee bee found to fight againſt God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="questions">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:24"/>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:44290:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>QVERIES for the People called QVAKERS.</head>
                  <p>FIRST,</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether are you willing that the depth of your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion or opinion touching Jeſus Chriſt his being now contained in the Heavens, the raiſing of our dead bodys after natural death, the Tryal of Spirits and Doctrins according to the Scriptures, ſhould be clearly and openly known, and publiſhed?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Whether do you not by many of your ſayings (which admit of a double conſtruction) craftily hide your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion in many things from the ſight of ſome honeſt people, who take you to hold the ſame truth with beleevers in general, concerning Chriſt, the Scriptures, and the reſurrection of the dead? Do you not endeavour to make them beleeve, you hold otherwiſe in ſome things than you do? And is not this diſſimulation at the beſts or lying after the manner of <hi>Annanias</hi> and <hi>Saphira, Act.</hi> 5.8,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:44290:25"/>Thirdly, Whether your ſelves (even all of you) bee not men and women of ſinfull failings, and imperfections, as act thoſe Godly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple you cry down? Doth not the light within ſhew you this? If not,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.8.</note> tell us who are the perſons among you without their failings or imperfections? And how came they ſo to bee?</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Do you in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Congregations of Beleevers, as well look after thoſe things which are Commendable as thoſe things which are Condemnable in their practices? Do you not overlook the example of Chriſt in this, who in his meſſage to the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> writes in praiſe of the good things in them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2. and particularly that they hated the Doctrin of the<note n="*" place="margin">Are not ſome Churches now to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for hating evill doctrins?</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>?</hi> Though withall hee reproves them for leaving their firſt love, and <hi>Sard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> Church being reproved, ſome few names are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. Do not you on the contrary cry them down in general, without any mercy?</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Whether your declaring againſt inſtrumental teaching, yet going about divers of you, informing and inſtructing your ſelves and others, who are free to hear you; doth not diſcover a groſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction between your profeſt principles and practice, and plainly ſhew that you would have them hear none but you? and whether this be right to ſet them againſt inſtrumental teaching, to bring them to hear your declaring, as ſome of you call your ſpeaking, altering only the name?</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, Whether inſtrumental teaching bee unſuitable to the new Covenant? If ſo, Why did Chriſt being aſcended, appoint Paſtors and Teachers in the Church, to continue untill wee all come into the Unity of the Faith? &amp;c. thus ordaining Miniſters for the work, while work remains for the miniſtery. Did Chriſt burden his Saints with needleſſe appointments?</p>
                  <p>Seventhly, Whether the Scriptures you bring to oppoſe Goſpell Ordinances, do not ſerve only to make void Circumciſion, with other Ordinances of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law; and to witneſſe againſt walking after the tradition of men, with the carnall formall practice, or idolizing of true Goſpell Ordinances? All you ſay, making not at all againſt a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44290:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
practice of Church-Ordinances, as breaking bread, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting one another, &amp;c. wherein the Saints have the footſteps of the flock in the primitive times going before them, and the appointment of Chriſt for the continuance of theſe till his coming, which muſt bee underſtood of his perſonal coming the ſecond time, he being come in the Spirit with great glory, when hee gave thoſe Commands, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25, 26. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25.</p>
                  <p>Eightly, Whether it is not better to wait on God in his good old ways recorded in his word, expecting his work to be gradually carried on as the growth of a building, or of a plant, or child, ſo running with patience the ſpiritual race ſet before us? or as the manner of ſome is, to forſake the principles of faith (whereof the Saints have had ſo great experience) in hope to ſtart up ſuddenly from a low ſtature into perfection, by imbracing a new doctrine?</p>
                  <p>Ninthly, Whether Jeſus Chriſt hath not prayed for thoſe who beleeve through the word of the Apoſtles, according to <hi>John</hi> 17.20? And if ſo, Whether they are not in a good and ſafe way who beleeve ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly? And whether it be not better to credit their teſtimony ſo fully confirmed by the Lord, and acknowledged by the Saints for many generations, than to forgoe that, to imbrace,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.3.</note> and follow the ſayings of ſome of your company?</p>
                  <p>Tenthly, What is that faith which the Spirit ſpeaks expreſly, <hi>Some ſhall depart from in the latter dayes, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits, and doctrines of devils?</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1</p>
                  <p>Eleventhly, Whether that doctrine which in ſum is no more but <hi>LOOK TO THE LIGHT WITHIN,</hi> with a curſe upon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, and a bleſſing upon obedience thereunto; be that glorious Goſpel preached by Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, holding forth good news to all people? Or whether it bee not a reviving of the old do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Juſtification by works, wherein the myſtery of iniquity worketh to darken the grace of God, in juſtifying the ungodly without works freely, and to make void the ſufferings of Chriſt? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. and the 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:44290:26"/>Twelfthly, Whether the light that is in every man doth reveal Jeſus Chriſt as crucified for ſin, and riſen again? If ſo, How came it to paſs that ſo many ſtrict men among the Philoſophers,<note place="margin">Acts 23.1. Act. 26.9. 1 Tim. 1.13.</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf walking according to his conſcience before converſion, were igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of him?</p>
                  <p n="13">13 Whether you have not among you many who preſume to be Maſters, or Maſterly teachers, contrary to that word of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.10. in the true intent of it? Do they not uſurp authority over the judgement and conſcience of their followers, requiring them to beleeve and obey what they ſay, without asking their meaning, and examining their ſayings by the Scriptures? whereas Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded his ſayings, as occaſion was offered, and need required, to his Diſciples, and the <hi>Bereans</hi> are commended for ſearching the Scriptures daily, whether the things ſpoken by the Apoſtle were ſo, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.18, 19.36, 37, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">14 Whether it bee not high preſumption, and ſpiritual pride, for ſome among you to break Chriſts commands, and teach men ſo? and to judge (as many do) the ſecrets of mens hearts? and raſhly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge of mens converſations, to affirm that they have not the Spirit? If the Spirit of God witneſs with their ſpirits (as I doubt not but it doth with divers of them, you ſo judge) that they have the Spirit of God, and the work of regeneration witneſſing thereunto, may they not by your bold judgement to the contrary, know how to judge of you?</p>
                  <p n="15">15 Whether do you not eſteem the ſayings of ſome among you of equal authority with the ſayings of God in Scripture? and as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, or more to be beleeved, and obeyed without any inquiry, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they agree with Scripture or no? even although they plainly contradict the written word? Is it not an uſual thing with many of you, to travel up and down to and fro, far and neer, to the wearying of your fleſh, and neglecting your relations, in obedience to ſuch voyces or ſayings not warranted by Scripture, but contrary thereunto? yet in many things of this kind, wherein ſome of you ſeem to glory, the Papiſts themſelves out-ſtrip you, only, they are more modeſt than to go naked; And who hath required theſe things of any of you?</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:44290:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>16 Whether Satan that old deceiver (who often changes his ſhapes, being diſcovered in many of his old devices) may not now be expected to come in his beſt dreſs, as an Angel of light? and being diſcovered in his old Antichriſtian forms, and in rude ranting, now to come with power, and ſeeming purity, ſhewing ſigns and wonders, to ſeduce from the plain ſimplicity of the Goſpel of Chriſt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe deſcriptions of his coming, and working, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8, 9. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.22. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3.14? And if ſo, ought not all men to take heed how they beleeve every ſpirit, or powerful motion to bee of God? as alſo, how they hear,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.1.</note> and follow every Prophet that comes in ſheeps cloathing, and pretends to come with light? And are not thoſe in the way to be eaſily ſeduced, who are ſo taken with the fair covering, and outſide carriage of perſons, as to imbrace their principles without a ſerious ſpiritual Scripture-trial of them? Whereas we are commanded, <hi>If any man bring not this doctrine, receive him not,</hi> 2 Epiſt. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſimple beleeveth every word, but the prudent man looks well to his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> Prov. 14.15.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:27"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44290:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>By reaſon of the Authors abſence at the entrance of this Book into the Preſſe, and notwithſtanding all the care taken afterwards, many faults have eſcaped, ſome of the chief of which are here noted, the reſt thou art deſired to correct with thy own pen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>Errata.</head>
                  <p>IN the Epiſtle to thoſe in Babylon, blot out (And for) p. 1. l. 20. for alſo r. ſo, p. 2. l. 9. blot out ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, p. 4. l. 5. blot out ought, p. 5. l. 10. r. Jer. 51. l. 13. r. Iſ. 59. p. 7. l. 4. leave out from many promiſes to Beleevers. l. 9. r. ſince. l. 16. leave out that, p. 10. l. 10. for graces, r. grace, p. 20. l. 24. for light, r. like.</p>
                  <p>In the Margent of page the 11. read Religious Scots.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
